He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him,
and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints.
In hours
time many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to see and
to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young
host this live Colin show, focused on enchantment in creation.
union of the scene and unseen as made by God.
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, giant killers, dragon slayers.
You're listening to Lord of Spirits podcast.
My co-host Father Stephen Diyang
is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana,
and I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
in a Mayan's Pennsylvania.
If you're listening to a slide,
you can call in at 855 Afri-Dio.
That's 855-237-2346.
Matzka Trudy is taking your calls tonight,
And we're gonna get...
those in the second part of our show. So tonight, we're talking about baptism. And I'm very happy to
let you know that this is the first part of a series on the Holy Mysteries of the Orthodox Church.
So this may be at least seven episodes, maybe more, maybe less. This could be the rest of the show.
We could just keep going. That's true. That's true. I'm pondering that now. It's good. So
So yeah, so what is baptism?
How is it different from the ritual washings of the Torah?
What does it do? How is it related to circumcision? Why is the water so cold?
What does St. Peter mean when he says that baptism saves?
Someone told me earlier that that makes them uncomfortable
When someone is baptized is anything happening in the unseen world?
All good questions that we're gonna address, but first we're gonna start with
circumcision
We're not going to need a parental advisory though this time.
right father? Well, I am using alcohol and tobacco and firearms and that last one doesn't
even make sense. Like why would I do that during a night? Yeah, hard cast. But I can see my
little red phone is starting to ring over here in the corner. This is a there we go.
unexpected. Yeah, in Hatemail 2, Father Andrew Damick at AncientFace.com.
Yeah, but we are going to start with circumcision and we're not going to be describing the process
in detail.
No.
That's...
You can look that up if you need to.
Not germane.
We're going to be talking about what circumcision does in the Old Testament, starting in the
Torah, how it's seen and the role it played.
in terms of ancient Israel and second temple Jewish community.
And the reason we're doing that is that as we're going to see in a little bit,
the ideas surrounding circumcision form the foundation for the understanding of baptism.
Right.
once we get into the New Testament and the New Covenant.
So circumcision is sort of the foundational commandment, sort of the
or commandment, the first layer.
The first thing is that God tells them to do.
Right.
It's because it's given to Abraham.
And so, I mean, you could say, yes, technically before that God tells him to go to
canin but that's not a commandment for anyone other than him.
Yes, and it's not an ongoing thing. It's not a foundational. Yeah, right. Right. So this is a commandment that's going to be practiced by him by his descendants. Right. So it's a commandment in the sense of the
Commandments of the Torah and it's the first one by a long shot, right in terms of sort of a direct in particular
Commandment
This also doesn't mean that it's the first ethical rule. Yes, before this guy was given murder still bad
Right.
And it's not.
That's how we're saying.
Right.
There was still good at evil before this.
But this is the first commandment of that type.
Of the type that we're going to get many of later on in the Torah when the covenant is
given through Moses.
But it's worth noting that this one comes, you know, depending on your dating, at least
500 years before Moses.
Yeah
And so that means it has certain unique features as compared to those others.
And it's given in Genesis 17. And the commandment is not just for Abraham to circumcise himself,
right but to circumcise his household.
Yeah, which means lot is nephew which means is herdsman and shepherds
cousins servants right now this is before Isaac is born right or isch malen right yeah right
This is all the males and when they are born they are circumcised but
the commandment is is given here and
This commandment is so foundational
that as we talked about back in...
in our episode talking about priesthood,
this is part of how the priesthood is taken away
from Moses and given to Aaron.
This is where leadership that will eventually become
kingship and priesthood gets separated
is particularly related to obedience to this commandment.
Yeah, I mean, you can see this happening
in Exodus chapter four, right?
Where Moses fails to circumcise his sons
his wife.
ends up doing it, and it's really mad about the whole thing, threatening to kill him.
And it's not like spelled out in the text in the sense of, and so therefore God took
the priesthood from him, right?
It doesn't say that, but right after the incident where Zippura Moses' wife responds
to him in this way and does it immediately what you see next, happen next is God begins
speaking to Aaron in a completely different place.
Aaron's not with Moses out in
in the Middle East, and so there's a sense of God turning away from Moses in a certain
way, and beginning to deal now with Aaron.
So that's really, and Aaron then becomes the first high priest of Israel.
Right.
And then in that previous episode, we then talked about how in the Golden Calf episode,
sort of, eldership gets separated from priesthood, right?
Yeah.
And the priesthood gets given to the Levites.
we won't rehearse all that now.
But the key is that Abraham, when he's given that commandment of circumcision, he's also told to walk before God and be righteous, right?
To live in a righteous way.
But that's
The the circumcision commandment is not just part of that is not just sort of a sign of that right keeping
that commandment itself as we see with Moses is a primary issue of obedience or disobedience.
That it doesn't matter if Moses was trying to live a righteous life and just, oh, oops,
I forgot to circumcise my sons or, you know, and himself, or he just got squeamish, right,
and wasn't up to it, right?
This is treated as an act.
of disobedience to God.
Yeah, this is a big deal.
At a very basic level.
And so I'm not a prophet, nor the son of a prophet, but I know a lot of folks, and I know
that there are some folks listening to this who think they know where we're going with
this circumcision thing, and why we're bringing it up on the baptism episode.
I think we're going to say that baptism...
and replaces circumcision. Right. At the at the end of this. We are not. Yeah.
Yeah. Circumcision does not go away. Right. Hold on. Lift into the whole episode. Right. So,
this is not just like, hey, they used to circumcise kids. And now we baptize kids. And it's the same
thing, right? And usually that kind of, shall we say, a nuanced argument. Half
among our Protestant friends when they're arguing about infant baptism.
That's not at all where we're going.
Yeah.
So we are, we're going to take a much more nuanced approach.
So we tuned everybody.
We're going to start by,
I'm not going to do it.
Digging a little deeper into circumcision.
Okay.
I wanted to make a really bad pun, but you may not.
So part of that is then, since we're not doing that,
just sort of, oh, it replaces it, switch, right?
The other place where circumcision comes up in the New Testament,
maybe the most prominent place, if you're in the New Testament,
if you're
Protestant. The most prominent place where it comes up
in the New Testament aside from what we're going to go on to talk
about in terms of the relationship with baptism. The most
prominent place where it comes up is in the this entanglement
between Saint Paul and certain parties that's reflected in
Acts 15. It's reflected in pretty much the whole his whole
epistle to the Galatians. Right.
And so a lot of discussions, Christian discussions of circumcision, kind of just focus on this whole thing, right?
Yeah, right.
And on a particular reading of Axe 15, sort of both the position taken by our Baptist friends that there's no relationship between circumcision and baptism.
And the position taken by our more sort of Protestant
Reformation friends that baptism just replaces
circumcision are both based on the idea that circumcision
kind of gets dustbinned along with the rest of the
commandments of the Torah.
Yeah, right.
We've talked about that relationship many times.
Yeah.
And acts of teen and Galatians are often the place where they go.
This dispute is where they...
go to argue that it's dustbin. So this is part of a big part of the reason why we're
going to end up in a different place than either of those positions because it wasn't
dustbin.
Yeah, that's the Torah has been erased or nullified.
Yeah. Yeah. I mean, that's what Jesus said. Right. Wait a minute. That's what Jesus said.
happen. Yeah.
So, to understand what's going on with that controversy, we have to kind of understand what
it was about in the first place.
And the way it's often presented, frankly, doesn't make sense, historically.
Okay.
So the way it's often presented is that St. Paul is starting these churches in these
different Roman cities.
And in these churches, there are Jewish people and Gentiles, non-Jewish people who become Christians.
And the Jewish people in those churches think that the Gentile people in those churches have to get circumcised.
Right.
And that's what the fight's over.
And then once it's presented that way, they say, well, the resolution of this controversy
is that St. Paul wins.
the day it says, you don't have to be circumcised anymore. Yeah. And then when you get to St. Paul going
in sponsoring sacrifices at the temple for people taking an azurai vow, or St. Paul having St. Timothy
circumcised, people get really confused. Yeah, that doesn't make any sense. Why would he?
if he's, you know, if St. Timothy's already done what needs to be done.
Right. And so, and and not
top of that historically, Jewish people did not go around trying to get Gentile people
to be circumcised.
Okay.
Well, why would they...
Why would they...
I mean, which didn't...
Don't they want everyone to be a Jew?
No.
That's not part of the Torah.
This is a difference between what's outlined in the Torah.
We've talked about this some before on the show.
And many other religions, not all other religions, but many other religions.
Christianity obviously involves evangelism, right?
And Islam, likewise, involves.
But within the Torah, we've talked about how there were sort of, because God came to dwell
among His people in Israel and then in Judah,
that create
these sort of concentric circles of how close you were to God's holiness. And so the nation of
Israel was called to maintain a level of holiness higher than the other nations. Right. And then the
priesthood to a higher level than that and then the high priest to a higher level than that, right?
Because he was going to go into the most holy place once a year. And so they didn't think that the
The whole priesthood had to maintain the same level of holiness as the high priest.
Hmm.
Right.
The floor doesn't do this.
Different standards is part of the way the Torah has actually laid out.
Right.
Because it's how close you are going to draw to God.
And so, they didn't think that everybody had to maintain the same level of holiness as the
priests.
Right.
The priests had to maintain a higher level of holiness during the time they were serving
in the tabernacle or the temple, then they did when they weren't.
Thank you.
Right? The regular folks, right? So there is no like, hey, we need to go stop those Greeks
for meeting bacon, right? Like that didn't happen. Right? They should stop, they thought they
should stop worshiping demons and idols, right? But they didn't think they had to become
Israelites, right? That's not a thing, right? And it wasn't a thing in the
century, right? The first century, and I know we've talked about this on the show before,
most of the first layer of St. Paul's Gentile converts were what were called Godfears.
Yeah, Gentiles who liked to hang around synagogues and study the Torah, but not actually take on
the whole life of being a Judean. Right. And the Jewish folks were not trying to persuade them to do
that. In fact, they actively discouraged it.
Why would they discourage them from doing that?
Because they didn't think it was appropriate.
They thought that the Jewish way of life was something given to them by their God for
them that separated them from and distinguished them from the other nations.
And that didn't have to do at that time primarily.
again where
approach this from a Christian perspective where we're thinking about, right? Like, well,
you have to do this stuff to get into heaven, right? That was not on the table at all. They
weren't thinking that way, right? They weren't thinking that these Gentiles need to come and
get circumcised and follow the Torah or they'll go to hell. Like, that was not a thing.
Right.
Or no Jewish people in the Versailles who thought that way.
So, this raises the question, when we see this group, who acts 15 says is from the party of the Pharisees, right?
There are these Jewish Christians who want the Gentile Christians in particular to get circumcised.
So, what is going on?
Well part of what reveals what's going on is the way in which this dispute was settled.
by St. James, the Lord's brother, at what we call now the Council of Jerusalem in Acts 15,
when the apostles gathered to hear this. And what happens there is that, say, James ends
up taking a very literal and strict reading of the Torah, specifically of part of Leviticus
that is called
by scholars now the holiness code that starts in Leviticus 17 and runs to 23-24 people argue.
You got to write journal articles and dissertations. So they argue about where it ends. But
this portion of the holiness code, the vast majority of the commandments in it,
Moses has told say to the sons of Israel, this, this is what you must do. This includes food laws
and gloves all these things. But in four places it says, say to the sons of Israel and all those
foreigners and aliens who live among you, all those soldiers who live among you that they must
keep these commandments. So there's a subset of those commandments that apply to everyone
and not just to Israelites.
And...
Those four places happen to be not coincidentally with X-15.
The sexual immorality, as defined in Leviticus 18,
idolatry, and twice about eating and drinking blood.
Yeah, which, as we've said before,
has to do with idolatry.
Right, right.
It's those are the four commandments
And X-15 says apply to the...
Gentile Christians, right, from the Torah.
Yep.
So how does that help us with, so that means they're being treated as sojourners, they're
being treated as, they're still Gentiles with their Gentiles who have come to live among
us Jewish folks, right?
How does that help us with what the problem was in the first place?
Well, in that same part of Leviticus where it's laying out, these are the things that
the soldiers and the foreigners need to do.
It says, unless, actually I think it says, but if, but if one of those sojourners, one of those foreigners,
when those Gentiles living in Israel or Judah, if they want to eat the Passover, which is sort of the symbol of sort of full participation, right?
If you're eating the Passover, this means you're participating in the sacrificial system, you're participating, right?
want to do this, then...
that person has to be circumcised and become an Israelite.
Yeah, if you want to go all the way,
then this is the process.
Right.
And so this, okay, so then the question that I would have
based on that is,
you know, given what we've said before about the Passover
and Paska being the same thing,
that, you know, the Eucharist is essentially eating the Passover
within the Christian context,
Why does that not apply to everybody then?
Right. Well, that's precisely what caused the disagreement. Yeah. Right. Is that you now
have within the Christian community, right? So there was already a way of being, you know,
settled in terms of the synagogue of the Sabbath in terms of Gentiles being in and around
synagogue. Right. Right. But now we have this additional layer on the Lord's Day.
gathering together to eat the Eucharist, which is seen as the sacrificial meal, which is connected to eat.
The Passover, right? And at those Christian meetings, Jewish Christians and Gentile Christians are
coming together to the same table and participating in the same sacrificial meal. And so this is what
engages the disagreement. Yeah, so they're saying, look, you know, we're eating at the same table.
So come on, you guys gotta be circumsized because that-
this works. Right. And so the real question that's being decided in Acts 15 is about the status
of Gentile Christians. Right. By being Gentile Christians, have they become in some sense Jewish
and therefore would need to be circumcised. Right. Or are they still Gentile Christians?
Right. Are they Gentile, are they more like Gentile Sojourners? Right.
and the decision of the apostles is the second.
Yeah.
Right.
And so what this does,
what this functionally does in early Christianity, right,
is there is a new
Christian way of life
that is created for Gentile Christians.
What do I mean by that?
So...
Before pre-Christianity, we go to the third century BC, right? You have
Jewish people, Judean people, right, living as Jewish people, right? Keeping the Torah,
hopefully, right? Following, right? Worshiping the God of Israel. And then you have
pagans, right? You have Gentiles. So you have Greeks who are living as Greeks and worshipping
the Greek God.
and following Greek customs, which include things like sexual immorality and
these other things. And so when Christianity comes along, what St. Paul helps
forge is the idea that they can no longer live as pagans. They can't keep
worshipping the pagan gods.
They can't keep participating in sexually immoral behavior.
Right, they can't keep, et cetera, et cetera.
Right, they can't keep doing that.
But he's also not evangelizing Judaism.
He's also not saying you need to become Jews.
Yeah, and I mean, isn't this basically just a fulfillment
of the Old Testament prophecies that talk about all the nations
coming to worship Israel's God?
Right.
Right, and so the contours and shape of what that look like.
That's what's being formed here in St. Paul's ministry.
It's not the elimination of all the nations.
It's the transformation of the nations.
Right.
And this continues, I say it begins in St. Paul's ministry
because this happens every time Christianity comes to another culture.
Right.
So we're seeing in St. Paul's ministry coming to, for example, the Greeks and the Romans.
Right, but when St. Boniface brought...
the gospel to Northwestern Europe, right? To my ancestors, they could not continue living
as the pagans they were before. But they also did not become Jews or Greeks or Romans. But
within that evangelical ministry, a new way to be, this is anachronistic, but just for
expression. A new way to be Dutch was formed. Why Dutch? We were still stingy. Except with the church.
Except with the church. But we had a cease with the pagan God worship. We had to cease. So it wasn't that
stop to being who we were, right? But what it meant to
be who we were changed.
Because what it means to be a Greek Christian is not the same thing that it meant to be a
Greek pagan.
Right.
And there were a first group of Greek Christians who St. Paul was writing letters to and trying
to help sort that out, what that means.
What can stay and what can go.
So that was the core of that controversy.
It was a-
controversy about Jewish identity and the particular commandments that are
related to Jewish identity. And those are the things that St. Paul and his
writings is going to call the works of the law, the works of the Torah. Not
good works in general, not keeping commandments in general. The works of the
Torah are these things that were the boundary markers that made someone
Israelite.
and then made someone Judean, made someone Jewish.
Right, that's what he's talking about.
Yeah.
And that's why he's so keen to say that salvation is not based on those boundary markers.
Right, if it were that that would be saying only Jewish people find salvation.
Right.
Which they call, of course, is not saying, nor were any other Jewish people at the time saying that.
But um...
So the boundary markers are those issues.
That's what's under debate and what's being discussed.
And so circumcision comes into that as being
one of the primary commandments related
to those boundary markers.
So aside from that role that it eventually played,
what did circumcision do?
Now we're going back to Abraham.
Yeah.
Right.
to get some more pieces of what's going on.
Yeah, and I think it's especially worth noting, you know, as we said earlier, we talked about the way the Bible sets up narrative.
Like what comes right after what?
You know, it's not like a news program where...
Here is every event that happened.
Yeah, every event just has nothing to do with the one before it.
Right?
The Abraham story comes when, right after the Tower of Babel's story.
despite their being what.
How long between these actual events historically speaking maybe hundreds of years?
Well, it depends potentially
Potentially if I'm right that this is about the rise involved the Babylonian Empire
Abraham is kind of before
Interesting
But where this is not a hill
I'm but then we plan to die probably but the point being there's a very
There is a very deliberate reason. I may be wrong about what it is. I don't
I think I am or I wouldn't say it, but that's what I could be.
But there is a reason why we don't have any time lapse described
between the Tower of Babel and Abraham.
Right, there is a reason. If you look at a lot of ancient Jewish literature,
They notice that, and they combine the stories.
Yeah. They put Abraham into the construction of the Tower of Babel.
Right. Which I think there was that was based in part on a historical memory of the fact that the
great Ziggurat of Ur was being built during Abraham's day. Yeah. And that's part of how those two
things got mixed together. But people have noticed that is to say for thousands of years that there's
no time markers there.
Right.
And so that means that these two things are being deliberately set next to each other
for a reason.
Right.
Yeah, right.
That these are related.
Theorize about the reason.
So, Bable, the nations are scattered and separated.
The 70 nations are divided.
Angelic beings are appointed right to watch and shepherd over them
Right, and that's sort of what we've described as sort of the third fall of humanity.
This is sort of the last nail in the coffin of that.
And so Abraham's story is the beginning of the solution.
This is the place where God again draws near to humanity to begin to dig our way out,
to begin to repair.
That was what was...
broken. And this is also the beginning of therefore the creation of Israel. And notice,
God did do it, sorry Calvinus, God does not pick one of the 70 nations.
Right. There's not an election in that sense. Right. Like he doesn't look at the 70 nations
and choose one based on his own good pleasure and that is Israel.
He creates a new one. He creates a new one that did not exist previous to that.
And that creation takes a lot of time because he starts with Abraham in his advance old age with Sarah
And it takes centuries to get to nationhood in the Exodus.
Right.
But this is making some...
that before was not, right, that did not exist.
They were not a people.
He made them a people, right, as he reiterates several times
in the Old Testament.
And so what this means, though, is because this is a created nation, right,
that he is bringing into existence, starting with one, with one man, right,
that the structure of it is...
intergenerational and family-based. This is based on extended family, originally, with Abraham
and the patriarchs. Abraham Isaac Jacob, Jacob sons. But also even when Israel is a full-blown nation,
right, and Israel and Judah are two separate full-blown nations, they're still structured according to
to extended families that are part of clients,
clients that are part of...
of tribes, right, and these units are intergenerational familial units. And this is one reason why
circumcision, right, that is something done to Sons, right, is a generational ritual, right,
it is particularly appropriate in demarcane because of this.
familial familial structure.
So this is just basic to circumstances we've already talked about it as boundary marker,
but as also as designating this family, forming this family that previously was not,
this is done in part through circumstances.
So it's not just accidental or because at eight days old you won't remember it or some
that this is done to children, right?
The circumcision happens to children.
But note is also, right, circumcision
shows us something important, even though there
is that familial relationship.
So it's a father circumcising his son, right?
It's the head of the extended family
who's performing the circumcision on the other males, right?
So there is this familial structure.
The fact that there is this commandment means that it is not strictly a familial issue.
Yeah, it's not just dad making a decision.
Right.
And it's not just, hey, you happen to be born in this family and that makes you an Israelite.
Yeah.
Right. The commandment has to be kept.
Yeah, there's a faithfulness thing going on there.
Right. You have to be faithful.
So this is when St. Paul talks about Abraham.
Right, and talks about circumcision. It talks about Abraham's faithfulness and it really should be translated faithfulness not just faith
But his faithfulness, right
This is part of what he's talking about right he's saying without the faithfulness
the biology the biological descent doesn't matter without the faithfulness
Hmm
Right, and he says this pretty directly in Romans 2
Yeah right where he's
says, I mean, this is, you know, as St. Peter says, sometimes St. Paul is hard to understand.
But this is the way it says in Romans 2.25, for circumcision, indeed is a value if you obey the law.
But if you break the law, your circumcision becomes un-circumcision. So it's bound up with that
notion of faithfulness. It's not, yeah, it's only valuable if you're actually doing something.
Right, right. So if, you know, the fact that
when you are eight days old, you are circumcised by your dad. If you proceed to live a life where you
violate all the commandments of God, that ain't helping you. You're breaking all the commandments of
God that you might as well be uncircumcised. So the other obvious element of this, when we're
We're talking about boundary markers and this kind of thing is that women, obviously,
aren't circumcised. Right. So this is so does that mean women are like the
heathen? Right? Or no? Quick answer. So the way the way that this works is that
someone who is right the wife or other female member of a household, right,
because we talk about servants, I'll kind of...
folks are included in this. Right? That person, right, that woman, that female adult human
is made in Israelite or later a Judea or a Judean by their relationship. Right? If we talk
about a wife by being the wife of a circumcised male. Right. That makes it part of the
because the idea here is that
that the man by receiving circumcision, right?
What he is doing is he is sanctifying himself.
He is setting himself apart, right?
And we're gonna get into that a little more here.
So he's setting himself apart
and he's doing that for and with his family.
Yeah, I mean, I think part of the reason why
it might be hard for us to parse this is because
Modern people tend to think in individual
holistic terms, right?
That you're not a member of something
by virtue of another relationship you have.
You're either a member individually or not, you know,
but that's not how it's actually set up in the Torah.
Right.
And, or the New Testament for that matter.
Yeah, right.
Right, because St. Paul applies this same logic to baptism
when he talks about people who are married
to unbelieving spouses.
Right?
Yeah, I mean, I think you probably tend to read that
as well maybe your influence.
wants them to make their own decisions.
Right, but that's not what he says.
It's not what he says, right?
He says that the faithful spouse sanctifies,
makes holy the other spouse and the children.
And he there is applying it to baptized men
and baptized women.
Because most of the early Christians
were women in slaves.
So it was far more common in the community's St. Paul
That's right.
writing to, for there to be a Christian woman married to a pagan man, then vice versa.
Right.
In fact, vice versa almost never happened because if the man became a Christian, the woman
was going to be a Christian in that culture, regardless.
So he applies it in both the same logic in both directions.
So this isn't something that just goes away.
Christianity did not become individualistic.
in the New Testament. Christianity became individualistic in Western Europe in the 16th century.
Said your hate mail to Father Andrew Damay at www.hatemail.com.
Some people think that's a good thing though. Some people think the individual is a good thing.
So why circumcision?
Right? Why this particular thing?
Right. I mean, there are lots of visible things you could do.
Right. You could have people wear beards and men wear beards are not wear beards.
You could have men wear their hair in a certain way.
You could have them, you know, cut off the last knuckle of their pink left pinky, right?
Right.
There's all these different things you could hypothetically do to indicate
that a person is set apart, right?
Or, or this kind of thing.
So why this in particular?
Right.
which is painful, right, which is, you know, definitely it
are in our post Victorian age, seen as unseemly to even talk
about in any detail. And you had a note on that from
apparently something. Yeah. Someone suggested to you.
Yeah, um...
Right. I mean, someone asks, I'm sorry, I'm getting a little lost here. Yeah, we're having
issues, by the way, everybody streaming on YouTube. Of course, if you're hoping to find us
on YouTube, you're not hearing me say this. So I don't know. But yeah, I mean, like some
Some people might wonder about what's called female circumcision, right?
Well, not where I was going.
Yeah, yeah.
Well, okay.
Anyway, that was one of the notes that I had, but.
Oh, yeah.
That is not the same thing.
Okay, okay.
Well, we don't have to,
we're not gonna describe what that is.
Yeah, right.
I mean, but I think it's not new.
Yeah, we've, I mean, I think we've covered that
in the sense of talking about how the relationship
actually works in the Torah.
That's a completely separate thing that's not practiced
in Israel.
Yeah.
I think this was more somebody asked,
You said somebody.
We asked about the garments of skin.
Oh, yeah, right.
That had something to do with.
Yes.
Yes, right.
Yeah, we actually did have a question about this in our Facebook group.
Yeah, thank you for reminding me.
Which was, you know, is circumcision a kind of ritual removal of the garments of skin?
Which, you know, which we've talked about, right?
So God gives mortality to mankind in the wake of the, you know, the events of Genesis 3.
And that mortality is given to him to enable him to repent.
We talked about this in our fall of man episodes and the first one, I think.
And the problem with seeing circumcision as the ritual removal of the garments of skin
is that would mean you're literally removing your ability to repent.
Which why would you then give all kinds of commandments in the Torah of how to repent?
If you've literally removed your ability to do that from the get.
go. Right. So no, that's not what that is. But you know, I mean, I can see why someone
might might think that because is the removal of some skin, but no, it's not, it's not the
garments of skin. So. Right. And the garments of skin are not a bad thing. Yeah, no, no.
Right. The garments of skin are this enabling of repentance. So it's a different
Sometimes, like if you look at
narcissistic sources, they talk about the
gun.
of skin meaning to mean materiality or like having a physical body or a material body, right?
And just to be clear, that's not what we're getting at, right? This is a beneficial thing,
ultimately a beneficial thing as we talked about when we talked about death ultimately being given,
if you read Genesis 3 closely, being given as a grace to humanity, not as a punishment.
But so then.
know why we're not talking about garbage of skin, you know, there's skin involved.
There's skin in the game as it were. But
very clearly, circumcision involves something being cut off.
Right. Right. And I've been told that the first cut is the deepest.
Okay.
I did it. I'm sorry. Yeah, I'm not sorry. I won't lie on the air. I'm not sorry.
But something is being something is being cut off. Yeah. So other than the obvious,
what is being cut off? Well, this is given remember first to Abraham. And Abraham
Remember is called out of or of the Caldys.
Is what is what we're...
told in Genesis. As we mentioned back in the Abraham episode, or of the Caldese is an
anachronism. The term Caldian for Babylonian comes from the neo-Babolonian empire, which is like
1500 years later. So why though is that anachronistic term used here in Genesis? Well, it's used to again
connect the urr out of which the city out of
of which Abraham is called to Babylon.
Yeah.
Right.
As we were just talking about with the Tower of Babel.
And so there is a division, as we were talking about
in the Torah between the nations, the 70 nations,
the world out there, over against Israel.
And Abraham is called out of these foreign nations
these foreign nations that have been
dominated by demonic powers.
Including where he came from.
Yeah, so it's a ritual participation in coming out from the nations.
Right. And Joshua's final speech in Joshua, he makes it very explicit that
even within Abraham's household, as he left,
or many members of his household were still idolaters.
Hmm, right. They were still kind of immersed in that.
And we see things don't go so swell for a lot.
Like, you kind of start creeping back over into a city.
Right.
Yeah, the wrong places, too.
I mean, like really, idolatrous places.
Right.
And so we have a cutting off, right, which is an acting Abraham,
or Abraham at the time, cutting himself off from the world
and the world off from himself, being separated from it,
being separated from it.
And that...
That's, you know, holiness is about being separated from evil, right?
And so there's the cutting off why the genitals in particular, right?
Yeah.
I mean, it seems a little sensitive.
Like why that, you know, like why not the last knuckle of your left pinky, right?
Right.
I mean, you could spare that, maybe.
Yeah.
Or your ring finger if you're joining the essentially.
But this is because the genitals very obviously this is connected to that intergenerational familial character of what's being done.
Yeah, there's a nation being made.
Right. And it's being made in this context of families and tribes and clans and obviously, right?
This is where babies come from, right?
This is it.
How they get made and so that seems to be the connection there sort of ritually
Something that I don't think people have noted enough about circumcision
Which ought to jump out at orthodox people
But I don't think does as much is that circumcision was done on the eighth day
Right.
The eighth day.
Normally, when you say V-
8th-
You
day to Orthodox people, you know, their eyes line up. But this is connected to that
eighth day symbolism, right? The seven days of creation, and there's the eighth day, right?
The beginning of a new creation. And so the circumcised person becomes a new creation
who was part of this new creation of Israel was made up of these newly created families.
right, um, we designated families. And again, there tends to be in certain bad theology, um,
it's tendency to say, well, okay, this old testament stuff, this old covenant stuff,
it's all about this physical material stuff. And then you get to the new testament and the stuff
get spiritualized.
Yeah, or like, you know, well that was all works righteousness.
But then you were given the righteousness of Christ, you know?
Yes, the Sveja.
And so this is why we can dustbin circumcision
and all those kinds of commandments and things, right?
But no, no.
But if you read, if you read the Old Testament,
beginning with the Torah itself carefully, right?
So if you read, for example, Deuteronomy 10, 12 through 17,
Deuteronomy 30 verse 6.
And then the Prophet Jeremiah returns to this,
and Jeremiah 4 verse 4, and Jeremiah 9 verse 26,
those Jeremiah chapter numbers are,
you're non-orthodox study Bible version of Jeremiah.
He talked, those passages talk about
the circumcision of the heart.
Yeah, right.
It's being what's truly important.
Yeah, stop skipping parts of the Bible people.
Yeah.
So.
This isn't some new spiritual, I say in the New Testament.
This was always true that the real circumstances,
it was a circumcision of the heart, your heart, your soul being cut off from
the world, the flesh, the devil, right?
And it being cut off from them and then being cut off from it, right?
It being kept holy and separate and apart, right?
is always what the aim was of the physical
So when we get to Christ himself, though we don't talk about it as much for reasons that are
probably obvious, again, post-Victorian squeamishness, we celebrate the Feast of Christ's circumcision
on January 1st.
Right.
Also the Feast of St. Basil.
when the kids look at the icon and say,
why does that priest have a knife?
Well, I've never been to a church
that actually had that icon out.
They always have the icon of Saint Basil.
So we've got, so here in a mass,
we have one icon that is both.
Oh, okay.
It's got both Saint Basil on it.
And I mean, there's sort of separate scenes as it were.
Yeah, that would be weird if they inserted Saint Basil.
Yeah, that would be a little odd.
But I mean, maybe that exists somewhere, I don't know.
No, but yes, it's got him.
on there and it's got the scene of the circumcision of Christ. You see that, you know,
that his mother holding him as a baby and you see the priest with a knife off to the side.
Yeah, so yeah. And this isn't just an incidental thing where somebody sort of did the math
and was like, okay, wait, so if Christ was born on the 25th, then that would mean he got circumcised.
Right. Like, yeah, right. We hated other feasts, right, for some reason.
This is big.
because, as you know, if you've listened carefully to the epistle reading,
let's read it that service, St. Paul actually talks about Christ's
circumcision. Yeah. Yeah. And so this is actually
theologically important, right, Christ's circumcision, to
understanding all of these issues we've been, we've been talking about.
So why is this relevant? Well...
So in understanding one of the sort of trajectories, one of the ways in which St. Paul presents Christ's death,
and it's not coincidentally that he presents it this way in his epistle to the Galatians,
which is where he's talking about this whole dispute about circumcision.
Yeah, right.
This is not a coincidence.
is for example in Galatians 3 verse 13 where he talks about Christ becoming it.
curse. Yeah, right. So he writes, Christ redeemed us from the curse of the law, by becoming a curse for us, for it is written,
cursed as everyone who was hanged on a tree.
And as we've talked about before back in the blessings and curses episode,
the curse of the Torah here that we're talking about is, for example, in Deuteronomy 28 through 30 where the blessings and curses of the covenant are set out.
Yeah, it's it's it's
Suffering the effects of sin.
Right.
The effects of sin.
These are the things that are going to happen
when you don't keep the Torah,
when you don't keep the commandments.
Right. Here's what's going to,
all these bad things are going to happen.
The sky's going to become like iron,
the ground's going to become like bronze,
meaning you're not going to be able to get any crops out of it.
You're not going to get any rain.
Right.
All of these things that will happen.
And so as
St. Paul quotes there from Deuteronomy, everyone's hanged on a tree is under a curse, and so Christ's
crucifixion in particular, that he is crucified, points this reality of Christ becoming a curse,
meaning Christ voluntarily suffers the effects of sin. That curse is state that results from sin.
Right? Christ takes that upon himself. And how is that ultimately described? That state of
in the Torah and the rest of the Old Testament is being cut off from among the people.
You are cut off. That's the number one way in the Torah in which the death penalty is described.
When someone is going to be stoned to death for some unrepentant sin that requires that,
it's there to be cut off from among the people. And I think we've talked before on the show how
when cut off from among the people occurs in those passages.
in the Pentateuch, it's not clear whether it's talking about death or exile because those were seen as being the same thing.
Yeah, it's ambiguous.
Right. But so Christ suffers the curse in being cut off when he is crucified.
But even though Christ is cut off in his death in the crucifixion, right?
he is not cut off from God. Right. Right. Because he is God. Yeah, sorry bad
readings of his comments on the cross. Yeah. We're supporting the solemn. He is
praying a solemn people read the rest of it. Anyway. Yeah. Right. He is not cut off
from God. And so what does that mean? Right. Well, because Christ is not cut off
from God and therefore not
truly cut off from life. Right? What happens is when he is cut off from the world is that the world
essentially has cut itself off. Right? It's like the world is sitting on the branch and it
saws off the branch behind itself. Right? And this is the world is in that system. Right? That world
system.
and St. Paul, not coincidentally, later in Galatians, sort of applies it exactly this way, right?
In Galatians 614.
Okay. Yes. Where it says, but far be it for me to boast. Yeah, there's a famous passage.
He's all famous really.
But far be it for me to pose.
except in the cross of our Lord Jesus Christ by which the world has been crucified to me and
I to the world. Right? So that's that, you know, again, that's sort of being dead to the world,
but the world is dead to me at the same time. There's this distinction. Right. That being cut off.
Right? And so this cut off, right, rather than being truly a curse, right, becomes a blessing,
becomes essentially holiness.
Right, becomes sanctification.
Right, becomes this sort of holy separation.
And then that carries with it.
And say Paul famously says in second Corinthians 517, if anyone is in Christ, he's a new creation.
The oldest passed away will hold the newest come.
So that new creation element of the eighth day, right, likewise comes into effect.
And so...
So this is what happens with Christ.
The crucifixion is therefore in this sense, St. Paul applies this language and understanding
of circumcision to it.
How is that benefit?
That becoming a new creation?
How is that applied to those in the church, to those in the Christian community, especially
those in the Christian community who are uncircumcised themselves.
Yeah, because there's, I mean, not too far down the road and it's most of them.
Right.
Yeah.
So how does that come to them?
Because St. Paul is arguing in Galatians that it does not come to them by those Gentiles being circumcised.
Yeah.
Right.
I mean, there's like, I think, well, it's right here in our notes.
uh but i mean yeah so second Corinthians 517 right if anyone's in
Christ, he's a new creation. The oldest past way behold, the new has come. So there's a difference
that's happened on a fundamental level. You know, it's a new era in a real sense.
Yeah. But the way that then gets applied to the Gentiles is explicitly for St. Paul through
baptism. Yes, which in what do you know is also their relations. Yeah.
Right? Where he says that in Christ Jesus, you are all sons of God through faithfulness. Right?
So again, this idea of forming a family, right?
For as many of you as we're baptized into Christ have put on Christ.
Right? So you've received this through baptism. Right? Baptism though does not, any more than
circumcision did, does not obviate faithfulness. Right? It's not that, oh, I was baptized. I don't
don't have to worry about any
other commandments, any more than being circumsized because you did not have to worry about any other
commandments. So faithfulness is still there, but baptism is the beginning of that. And he goes on to say
in Galatians 3, there's neither Jew nor Greek, there's neither slave nor free, there's neither
there's no male and female for you all are all one in Christ Jesus. And if you are Christ, then you
You are Abraham's offspring and heirs according to the promise.
Yeah, which puts it again.
firmly back into that faithfulness definition of what it means to actually be part of the nation.
Right. And so through baptism and through faithfulness, like Abraham's faithfulness, that is the way in
which these Gentiles, these Gentile Christians become Abraham's offspring. That is how they become
part of the family of God, not through being circumcised and becoming Jewish. And again,
and see.
Paul points to more than once in Galatians and Romans that Abraham is prophesied to be the father of many nations.
Yeah, not just one nation that everyone's getting added to, but
there's I mean, it's dual, right? So on the one hand, he's the father of many nations, but on the other hand everyone who is
his
offspring is Israel
So it's part of his family. Yeah, it's part of this. Right. Right. Right because
For St. Paul, Judah or Judea and Israel are two different categories.
Yeah.
Right.
So, when he talks about Judea and Judeans, which the word that gets translated as Jews in a lot of our modern translations, English translations, is actually Judeans.
And so when St. Paul talks about the Judeans, he's talking about Jewish people, he's talking about a particular group of people.
This particular group of people. When he talks about Israel, he's talking about the whole family of God.
Because, remember, Judea was not all of Israel in the Old Testament.
One tribe.
Well, it includes the nation of Judah, includes the Benjaminites and some Levites.
But it's still a subset.
Yeah, right.
The Northern...
kingdom of Israel, right, had the majority of the tribes, right? And we won't go into
all this now. I don't future episode. It's a more detailed, but the connection, the particular
connection that Saint Paul sees between the Gentiles and the Northern Kingdom of Israel.
But the idea here is that Israel as the people of God is this larger, more inclusive category,
Whereas Judeans, Jewish people is a particular group.
right? They aren't just synonymous in the way he's using them in his letters.
And so the baptized Greek, right? The Greek Christian in Corinth is still a Greek.
He is not now Jewish, right? He is still a Greek. He is a Greek Christian, right? The difference is
has to do with how he lives his life.
because as we said, there is this new thing forming,
which is what it means to be Greek and Christian,
opposed to Greek pagan.
You can have both identities at once,
but one of them is radically altered by the other.
And that's what we might think of as an ethnic designation,
is radically altered by being Christian.
Right, right.
And this is reflected, for example, at the very end.
of the book of Revelation, where the people from all the nations come into the New Jerusalem
and they all bring with them the treasures of those various nations.
Hmm.
Wow.
Nothing.
I was going to say reminiscent of the looting Egypt.
Yeah.
You know, image.
Yeah, but explicitly nothing unclean or impure can enter in, right?
So all of the
garbage of the various nations, right, is all of the sinfulness, all the uncleanness,
that gets left behind.
And the treasures, right, the gold, the silver, what is pure, what is holy, that gets brought
into, right, the family of God.
And so there is a place that I already alluded to, right, which occurs in the epistle reading
for the Feast of Christ's circumcision.
It's actually Colossians.
where St. Paul really pulls all of these ideas we've just been discussing together all in one place.
Okay. Yes, so Colossians chapter 2
verses 8 through 12
St. Paul says,
Seed to it, that no one takes you captive by philosophy and empty deceit according to human tradition
according to the elemental spirits of the world and not according to Christ
for in him the whole fullness of deity dwells bodily
and you have
been filled in him, who is the head of all rule and authority.
In him also you were circumcised with a circumcision made without hands by cutting off the body
of the flesh by the circumcision of Christ, having been buried with him in baptism in which
you were also raised with him through faithfulness in the powerful working of God who raised
him from the dead.
So here, we have very clearly the benefits of Christ.
circumcision are bestowed upon these Gentiles in Colossi explicitly through baptism.
Yeah, so it sets up the same relationship as being the wife or daughter of a circumcised man
in the old covenant, you know, because the church is the bride of Christ, and so therefore
the relationship in this in these terms is the same. Christ's circum...
in the same position counts for the church.
And this is why Hebrews,
several other places,
talk about Christ sanctifying himself
before his crucifixion.
And those are weird passages
and people kind of don't know
like Christ was holding the whole time, right?
Why did he have to sanctify himself?
What is it?
This is talking about that him being set apart
so that that can be bestowed upon us, right?
As his bride through his circumcision.
So this is the ultimate argument from St. Paul as to why Gentile Christians not only don't
have to get circumcised to be able to receive the Eucharist and be full participants in Christian
right ritual life but should not be.
Because for St. Paul, by demanding that they be circumcised individually in the flesh,
as he says, that would be
replacing Christ's circumcision for St. Paul with their own.
Yeah, it would be like, if you were baptized in the church,
and then you decided to go get your own baptism somewhere else
because you felt like it wasn't.
Right. It wasn't.
It didn't really do the job or whatever, you know?
It would be saying, I'm not going to be made holy by Christ.
I'm going to make myself holy.
Yeah.
And this is why this context St. Paul talks about people
trying to establish their own righteousness.
Hmm.
right rather than receiving the righteousness of Christ through faithfulness.
Yeah, it's not about...
Yeah, I mean, if you think about that, like people talk about...
He talked about people establishing their own righteousness, that's often, especially
in, in Reformation framework, is read as, you know, stop trying to do good things.
Christ has already done good things, but that's not what's going on.
It's the establishment of righteousness.
It's not just doing good things.
right and that righteousness is received through faithfulness. Yeah. Which involves keeping commandments.
Yep. If you love me you will keep my commandments at all. Which it says a gazillion times in the Bible.
Yes. Like just do a word search everybody for love and commandments and see how many places they
are paired together in the Bible. It's a bunch. A bunch. All right. Well with that said,
There was a good beefy first half we're gonna go
ahead and take our first break.
We'll be right back with the second half
of the Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Jesus's last words to his disciples were go
and make disciples of...
all the nations. Unfortunately, many parishes are struggling to follow this command.
In reclaiming the Great Commission, Father Evan Armitas offers a road map to help us get
back on track.
Relying on his 20 years of parish experience, holy scripture, and insights from research
and his visits with churches across the U.S., he discusses how you and your community can
implement changes that will transform, revitalize, and renew your parish. You'll learn how to
diagnose and remove the barriers you face. Deal with results.
to change. To find what a healthy parish looks like, lead with purpose and create a parish
health plan. Written for clergy, council members, ministry leaders, small groups, and all
committed parishioners. This book will help any church in its journey to reclaim the great
commission. Purchase it today at store.AncientFaith.gov.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick.
and father Steven DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back everybody.
If you could give us a call,
we're talking about baptism tonight.
And we actually got a question and email.
Someone was asking about infant baptism.
They were saying,
You know, if baptism washes away.
way sin, why would an infant who has never sinned need this?
And kind of related sort of questions that are, you know, in terms of seeing things in
a process in a way, for instance, like shouldn't the person baptized first believe in God,
have the self-effect power of baptism, why is there no profession of faith and that kind
of thing?
And I think that those questions larger are answered by the foregoing, but we'll kind
to flesh it out a little bit as as we go but
But I mean, these are important questions that people have.
And part of that is a reductionist thinking.
Yeah, right.
So repentance and the forgiveness of sins is part of, obviously, baptism.
And we're going to get into that somewhere here, right?
But that's not all.
Yeah, it's not all it is.
That's not.
Scripture says it does a lot of things.
That does it exhaust.
Right.
baptism.
about is about is just me being forgiven of my personal sins.
Yeah.
Again, that's a very individualized approach.
Yeah, and we got another question which is related to this too, right?
And then actually connects directly to what we were just talking about the end of the first half,
which is, I mean, it's kind of a sticky question, but it's like, you know, should people be baptized
when they become orthodox, even if they have been baptized before.
And if someone has been baptized, and that's for the church to determine whether that actually has happened,
then the answer is no. Right? Because of what we just said, you don't go and do it again.
And while this is not a show about the canons and how to apply them.
Because I don't think there are enough bishops listening, so that would be irrelevant.
We want to retire audience pretty much.
But yeah, but the truth is, is that if you...
actually do read the canons, they do not ever say it doesn't matter at all what anyone's
previous religious experience was, baptize them all, no matter what. They, in fact, the
canons say, well, these people, we do this with them, these people we do this with them,
these people in so forth, right? And it's largely kind of the question seems to be, do we
consider what they had before a baptism or not.
So, and that's me.
because they're trying to be careful not to baptize somebody twice.
That's the point.
I don't think that's inaccurate.
What you've said.
But I don't even think we need to go that far.
What did we say about circumcision?
It's an act of faithfulness.
Yeah, right.
It's an act of obedience.
And faithfulness and obedience doesn't mean I do what I think is right.
Right, I know what an irony.
right to, for people to come into church and say, look,
this is how I want to be received.
So this is basic, right?
Like, this is an act of faithful disobedience.
So, yeah, yeah, that's that individual is some rearing,
it's ugly head again.
Yeah.
Yep.
And it's, it's no good.
It's very bad.
No man is an island.
All right.
Here we are in the second half.
And we're going to take you to the river and put you in the water.
Yes, yes.
I mean, I'm hearing my head that great old song,
went down to the river to pray,
studying about that good old way.
I'll say I was going for talking hits.
But I know.
I was doing, you know, bluegrass whole time in music.
Yep.
That's the difference between you and me and all the students.
The irony is, you're the one who lives in the deep south.
I live up here in, well, Yankee land, I guess.
I am. I live in Cajun territory.
Yeah.
I recently learned is very small though, really.
So like Alexandria and Shreveport suburbs of Dallas, apparently.
Nice. Wow. That's like Charles suburb of Houston.
Wow. That's sharp.
I was going to say this though about Emmaus, Pennsylvania.
Here's a little bit of really obscure history.
in the very first land grants that defined Virginia,
where I live was actually included in Virginia
and as was most of the United States actually
and much of Canada.
But after I think about three years,
the line got moved just southwest of me.
So where I am now was Virginia.
So I do sometimes claim to still be living
in the state I was born in.
So.
Once upon a time this was the house. I used to try to get people to call New York New Amsterdam
You know the way they call the standable Constantinople, but
Yes, well people just liked it better the other way it got the works
Indeed and so point you know point out but everybody by the way that that's not a song original to they might be giants
No originally the four lads that is a Lysmer music classic. There you go. That's right
Clezmer is that the first time we bought-
Clashmer on Lord of Spirits?
Who knows?
I don't know.
We should try to come up with that more often.
Clasmer is a cool kind of music, everybody,
if you're not into it.
All right.
Well, yes.
Speaking of John the Baptist, but we digress.
We didn't really digress at all in the first half.
So I feel like we're doing digression.
Yeah.
You know, I don't need permission to digress.
Yes, I can digress freely, and it will.
That's true.
But yeah, so in this second half.
We are going to be talking about St John the Forerunner,
St John the Baptist, because how can you talk about baptism and not talk about
St John the Baptist?
As he's a father and Baptist?
Northern Baptist?
Well, on behalf of my grandmother, I would have to say general association of regular
Baptists.
What wanted a irregular Baptist?
I say what?
Then will the GARB age finally be ushered in?
Sorry.
It's an old joke from my childhood.
So as St. John is affectionately known by my fellow Dutch people, it's more like St.
John the Doeper.
Doeper, I know this is really, and isn't it dope?
D-O-O-P, isn't that baptism in Dutch?
Yeah.
Doep.
I'm sure it's etymologically related to dip.
It's so hot.
It's very dope.
Yeah, I mean, there are a bunch of obvious Amsterdam doper jokes that suggest themselves,
but we'll just pass over them in silence.
So say John the Four Runners in the wilderness, he's at the Jordan River.
He starts baptizing people at the turn of the era.
So what's he doing?
What would the people at the time have understood what he was doing?
Because in a sense, this sort of comes out of nowhere
in the sense that there aren't people getting baptized
per se in the old testament.
Right?
I say per se because we're going to see there are some...
things. But there are some incidents where people who are being healed are getting into the Jordan
River, those kinds of things that are certainly connected. But the main context into which the
baptism of St. John enters is into the idea of the various ritual washings that were common for
various purposes in its second-templar Judaism.
Yeah, of which...
there were a bunch growing out of right growing out of the the Torah itself right so
one thing we have to remember when talking about these is
despite how sometimes it's treated in terms of modern readings. Uncleanness and sin are not synonymous
Right. Unclean, unclean. I mean you could be unclean.
just by having leprosy. Right. You know. Right. Well, even far more simple things than that.
Yes. Right. Going to the bathroom. Right. Right. Yeah. Touching a dead body.
But even like things that might otherwise seem good. Like, right, doesn't touching
Torah scrolls. Render you, Richard. Right. Unclean. Right. Yeah. So any holy thing
that's out of its original kata is makes you unclean, right? It becomes unclean.
So, we have to divide between what are commonly called, in the scholarly taxonomies, ritual
uncleanness and moral uncleanness.
Okay.
They're related though, right?
They're related.
Yes.
So, ritual uncleanness is the broader category.
Okay.
Right.
So, this broader category includes like the things we were just mentioning, going to
the bathroom.
bodily emissions for men and women, right?
Bleeding.
Touching a dead body.
Even if you're doing something good
like going to bury a family member, right?
Yeah, but coming into contact to clean the body
and prepare it for burial, right?
You've touched it, you're now unclean.
All of these things, those make you ritually unclean.
And the reason it's called ritual uncleanness
is that then there is a ritual washing
that you undertake.
Yeah, right before yeah, I was gonna say because well, yeah, like you said there it has to be undertaken
But and and the reason is that the unclean is is not just sort of a state of being
Bad or dirty or whatever. It's that something needs to be done
Right, it doesn't mean you're guilty of something right. It doesn't mean you need to repent of having God to the bathroom
Right
But again, this is not sin.
Right, but there's a washing that needs to occur.
Right, right.
And then that then remedies it.
And that's, you have to perform that washing
before you go deeper into those concentric circles
we were talking about.
Yes, approaching God.
Right.
And so if you're gonna approach God,
if you're gonna go deeper into those concentric circles,
you need to, to ritually wash, to remove that,
uncleanness, right?
Um, um, the other
Another category is moral uncleanness, meaning subset.
You have committed sinful acts.
In addition to the way that those sinful acts have to be dealt with, they also make you
richly unclean.
There needs to be both repentance and washing.
Touching a dead human body makes you richly unclean, making a dead human body by killing
someone makes you morally unclean with
includes ritual ungliness. Right? And so that has that added element of repentance. Now, it is
possible, someone who is ritually unclean, who does not perform the ritual washings before going
deeper into those concentric circles, right, can contract moral uncleanness by virtue of that.
Right.
So
So for example, if you're a Nehdaab and Abahu, Aaron's sons and you're drunk and messing
around and you go into the temple in that state, you're going to be on fire for the Lord,
and not in the good way that you want to be.
It took me about two seconds for that joke to sink in.
Yeah, so you're waving at me right?
So it could become that, right?
But so obviously, the deeper in you are
in those concentric circles, the more often
you're going to have to participate
in these ritual washings.
So priests are having to do this much more frequently,
because they're going to go and serve.
And they have to maintain this ritual cleanness,
all the time.
And moral cleanness, obviously, also as well.
And
the high priest then most of all.
And so because of the need for this,
we have archeologically we found.
So at the time when you get to,
first century BC, first century AD,
there are huge communal baths essentially in Jerusalem
for pilgrims who are coming to the temple
for Passover or for the other feasts.
And when I say huge communal bad.
this is what this looks like, right, in terms of the excavations. Imagine like an
Olympic-sized swimming pool. Okay. And on each of the long sides of the rectangle,
there are stairs, stone stairs leading down to the bottom of the pool. Okay. So that
pilgrims come in a group, go down the one side into the water, and then walk up
the stairs on the other side.
having like pass through it.
Yeah, so the idea is to, so that lots of people can go through this all at once.
Right.
So when you have thousands of pilgrims, right?
Coming off the road and whatever they've been doing and all that and now coming to,
come into the temple courts, right?
They can pass through there and perform that ritual washing in an efficient way, right?
Yeah, because otherwise this is stuff that you would just do privately for various kinds
So
But when you've got all these people coming at once, you need to figure this out logistically.
Yeah, it's not like one of those places with one metal detector, right?
Where each person has to go and wash and you have to wait, right?
That would not be functional, right?
They're like the airport.
Right.
This is the TSA pre-checkvert now.
And the idea here, right, at the core of it, is that when one comes and presents one's
and present ones.
self to God, you present yourself to God clean and whole. Right. And that whole is where
like the bleeding and the emissions of those kind of things come in, right? Because you're
seen to be depleted. Yeah, right. Right. And I mean, this is, in the case of bleeding, this
is literally true, right? Like you bleed, you lose some blood, right? And it takes time
for that to write.
regenerate. Yeah, but so that's the idea behind it. Right. And and this is still,
right, this is still in our tradition. If you pick up a cop, be at least of the
idiotic archdioceses pre-schied, right? There's hygiene rules for priests in
there. Yeah, right. And I mean, you know, and there's even like in some, some
additions of the liturgic on you got the commandments of St. Basil of Priests of the
beginning which relate to some of this stuff. Yeah, there's the tradition of
watching his hands. Yeah, the Bishop watches his hands celebration of the
energy. The proske of the where we cut the bread and the wine, you know, cut the
bread and pour the wine. There's a washing that happens before that. And
yeah, I mean, you know, traditions about, for instance, clergy and and traditionally
frankly, anyone who's going to receive communion, abstaining from marital
relations tonight.
before. So there's all these ideas of preparation and, you know, sitting
apart and like the fasting rules connected with the communion are related to
this as well. Right. And again, this is not because there's something evil about
those things. Right. Right. That's this has to do with how we come and
present ourselves before God, right, in worship.
So
So, in terms of what St. John is doing, in terms of, you know, pushing people under the
water, right?
This is, you know, it's within this context of ritual washings.
So the people who see him doing this are going to understand this within that context of ritual
washings, right?
Yes, they've seen this before.
But there are also features of what he's doing that separate it from...
just sort of the regular run of the mill, right?
Washings that we were just talking about, right?
I say run of the mill because they were
happening continually, right?
Yeah.
In the life of people who are trying to follow the Torah.
So St. John is doing this out in the desert.
And the immediate significance of that that you might see
is
that the purpose of the ritual washings was to allow you to draw near to the temple, right,
to draw near to where he got, he's actually having people do this, he's calling them
further away in order to do this. Yeah, that's weird. Right. So there is in what St. John is doing,
there is an inversion going on. What he's doing is inverting the way in...
which most Judeans would have at least wanted to see themselves. Because he's calling the
people out of Jerusalem and out of the other cities of Judea and Galilee and Samaria,
calling them out to the Jordan, right? He's calling them to remove themselves from the world,
but the world here is Jerusalem and these other huge cities.
which what does that say about what's Jerusalem?
status and status of the temple there. Right. It's treating Judea as the place of sin. So it's
treating Judea like Egypt in the Exodus or like Ur when Abraham is called. Yeah. And Herod's temple,
which is the temple that's standing there at the time, right, is being treated not as the place
God dwells. Show me.
say right not as a holy place right and that is not unique in Second Temple Judaism as we'll see
here in a minute yeah right different groups within Second Temple Judaism had different relationships
with the Jerusalem Temple yeah yep but the juxtaposition here is that they're being called out of
what was supposed to be the Holy City this is supposed to be the Holy City the city that is Holy
and set apart, right? Jerusalem, Mount Zion, city on a hill, the original, right?
Yeah. Which, I mean, this kind of thing.
Like to the nations.
Why, why St. John was so unpopular with certain people.
Right.
Because what he was doing was fund a fundamental insult to the temple.
To the temple, to the priesthood at the time, which was the Sadducees, to Herod, right?
Yeah, yeah, it's good.
Here it realized that we could tell.
Yeah, this guy's a real rebel.
And so he's not only calling them out, but he's calling them to
this baptism that is not just about like forget, it's not
about forgiveness of sins, just the sense of like, hey, I
committed a crime. God's mad at me. And I need to go and get
baptized. And then I'm off the hook. Yeah, right. So I go to
and don't go to hell. Again, that's not in view.
here. Right? This is you need to be purified from the way of life you've been living. Right?
And the residue that's been left on you. Yeah, which explains why it says in the scriptures,
when various groups come to say, John, they often ask him, what are we supposed to do? Like,
Now that I've come and done this, how is my life supposed to change?
Right.
just go back. Yeah, right. He gives them specific commands. Yeah.
Okay, go back to just doing things like I did before. Right.
And he gives them what he says to them in terms of commands is ways to
remedy, right, that that way of life. Right. And so we read about
particular people in the gospels who were sort of not
interested. And yeah, it's a child's offer. Right. You need to take
You're gonna fall in.
That's a joke.
And one of those groups is at least many of the Pharisees.
Right?
Right.
There are particular examples of Pharisees who did receive St. John's baptism in the same
cosmos, right?
But for the most part, the Pharisees were not interested.
And you see that, for example, in Luke 7, verse 30.
Why were they not interested?
Well, the word Pharisee, and this is not 100% certain, but this is pretty much every scholar's
best guess.
comes from a word that means to be set apart.
So it'll be separated.
They basically like, we're already separated.
Right, they can...
Yeah, we're separated the good way.
Right, and that's why when you hear Pharisees speak in the Gospels,
they often refer to sinners as these other people.
Yeah, we're not them.
Right, so they have...
From their perspective, they already have this ambivalent relationship with Herod's temple.
Right.
This is what allows the Pharisees to survive the destruction of the temple.
Yeah, they had to find themselves over against it.
In terms of the Jews, they already had this sort of ambivalent relationship with it.
I say ambivalent because it's not like they never used it or wouldn't go near it or
anything.
But it was the temple but they acknowledged that the Sadducees running it and the way
it was being run was corrupt and needed to be purified.
There's good evidence they believe that the Messiah was going to do that when he came.
They weren't wrong.
Right.
Agreed.
Hey, you guys got this one right.
So but they had this ambivalent relationship already and for their perspective, what being
a Pharisee was all about was separating yourself from yes, that sinful way of life that unfortunately
is going on in Judea.
Right.
But we're the ones who are separate and therefore they didn't think they needed what St.
John was doing.
you
They thought they had already had that taken care of.
Many of them.
Sadducees, it might be obvious.
They weren't interested in looking at it.
Yeah, I mean, they're the establishment.
Luke 20 versus 1 through 8, right?
This is where the Sadducees had some Torah scholars
and some people come to Jesus to test him again.
and he kind of throws a question back at them, which is always bad.
for them. And they say, you know, by what authority are you doing these things you do? And he says,
well, on what authority did John baptize? Right? Was it from human or was it from men or from God?
And of course, they're like, well, if we say men, then all the people will get mad at us.
If we say God, then they'll ask, hey, why didn't you go get baptized then? So they just kind of
to water off, right?
Right?
But so this shows that they weren't interested.
I mean, they're the ones being denounced.
Yeah, yeah.
That's the high-prestly family.
These are the corrupt people who he's talking about, right?
Yeah.
And so, yeah, their number one, not super willing
to accept that they're corrupt and evil.
And number two, not going to change their ways.
Right?
So, yeah.
That seems to be why they weren't interested.
So we also talked about, we did a-
episode just on St. John the forerunner. Yes, what are my favorites? And in that we talked about
the whole idea of remnant theology as it's called now in scholarship but that idea that there's a
faithful remnant always preserved within Israel. Yep. And Judah going back to the prophet Elijah after
the showdown at Mount Carmel, right where he says, I'm the only one who's still worships the
trips you all the way to God of Israel.
Might as well just take my life and God says, no, you know, there are all these who have not bowed the need of bail, right?
That there's that remnant, right?
And how St. John, part of what he's doing is again reforming that remnant out there on the other side of the Jordan, right?
Putting that people, that family unit, right, to together again, so that he can then turn that over to Jesus as the Messiah.
Right.
And so this of course brings us to
Christ's baptism. Yes, finally. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So we move from Christ's
circumcision to Christ's baptism. Yeah. He shows up there at the Jordan at the
beginning of the Gospels, depending on which one you're looking at. Yeah. But all
four of them. Yeah. Right. So I got what important it is because there aren't a lot of
things that are actually in all four. But this is one of them.
And so, and we talked about this, we've talked about this a little bit before too, but
the St. John Accord is a protest at first, right?
Basically, he says, I need to be baptized by you, right?
Sort of acknowledging like, hey, the whole forgiveness of sins part and being added to the
faithful remnant and all this, like, you don't need that, right?
Yeah.
You're already there.
In fact, he says, I need to be baptized by you, right?
Meaning you're like above me, right?
Yeah, and you're the one through whom all of this
is really happening.
Right, right, in the first place.
But Christ says he's going to do it to fulfill all righteousness.
And so we see that there's another sort of inversion
happening here, right?
that Christ, when it comes to it again, we're
going back to this sort of uncleaness category
and this wholeness category,
when Christ goes and touches a leper,
he doesn't become unclean.
The leper becomes clean, right?
Leopards healed.
When he touches a dead body,
he doesn't become unclean.
The dead body comes back to life, right?
Right, because uncleaness is about your relationship to God.
It's about your ability to approach God.
and he is.
God. God approaching them. Yeah, he cannot become unclean because he's the goal of clean it.
Cleanliness. Right. Right. And so when Christ goes into the waters, right? The waters don't make him
clean. He makes the waters clean. Yeah. And all the language. And again, like I said, we'll just do
this briefly because we've talked about this on the show before.
The waters are purified. All the language in the feast of the
offening that we use, but the waters being purified, the
dragons there being crushed, right? The spiritual powers, the
waters. This is the the and all of the new creation language,
right? The eighth day, new creation language, the waters being
cut off, right? All of that language that we've been talking
about tonight. Get the attached to
sort of Christ's baptism as the beginning.
Yeah.
Right.
And so this also, right, this also is deeply connected to why St. John is doing this in
the Jordan and calling a people out there out of this sinful world, right, is that Christ's
name even though it drives me bonkers when people pronounce it.
Hebrew way. Got to admit people get mad at me when I say it. Right? The people who say,
Yeshua, Hama, Shea, good stuff. It's like, Bob, your grandfather's Norwegian. What are you doing?
But Christ does have the same name. The name Jesus is the Latin version of Joshua.
Yeah, the Latin version of the Greek version.
Yes.
Yeah. Well, anything in Latin is stolen from the Greeks. So often true. But they've Joshua, right?
And of course, when Joshua leads the people into the land, they do it through the Jordan,
in the Jordan parts in front of them, right? Insert all the language about the Jordan turning back,
which is lifted directly from Joshua.
in our celebration of the Feast of Christ, baptism.
Right.
And so what Christ is enacting,
the Jordan with St. John, as he takes this group of people,
this faithful remnant that St. John has gathered,
is a sort of reconquest.
Like the entrance into Canaan again.
Right. The land has become like it was.
Right.
Because...
the leaders, the authorities have become corrupt, right? Herod is like Pharaoh, he's going
around killing innocent children, right? And so this reconquest has to happen. And as we
talked about, the understanding at the time, we have all these exorcisms in the synoptic
gospels because they viewed those spirits as being the spirits of dead giants, meaning they're
the same beings who Joshua was.
driving out of the land. Yeah, and so this is the new literally literally the new Joshua
who literally has the same name. Right, right, who is now beginning this reconquest and the
re sanctification of the land by again this imagery of Christ sanctifying himself in order to pass
that holiness on too.
to the rest of us through our baptisms.
Yeah, I mean, I think we can underline enough the significance of the place,
that this is the Jordan,
that these same events that they continually celebrate in their liturgical life,
that they hear in the scriptures,
this is where John is doing what he's doing.
As if to say, hey, it's all happening again,
Although it's really happening in the
full as possible way now this time. This is the fulfillment of what Joshua was doing.
Right. And that fulfillment is part of what's going on, that the story in a lot of ways of the old
testament, and Christians have traditionally read it as a story that's leading up to Christ.
Obviously, Jewish folks not necessarily. We read it as a story of Christ. Part of it is the story
of
God creating and then sanctifying this remnant of the people to prepare for the coming of
the Messiah, the coming of Christ.
And part of doing that is that throughout the history that we see unfold in the Old Testament
is that these patterns are being elaborated.
rituals are being begun. These different things
are created in order that when Christ comes, those who have been faithful to what was established
will recognize Him, will be able to understand Him. When we talk about fulfillment, when
we talked about atonement and we were talking about the day of atonement and connecting
that to Christ, right? We're really asserting that the purpose of that day of Atonement
Ritual.
and participating in it annually was so that when Christ offered himself as a sacrifice
for the life of the world and for its salvation, the people would be able to understand what
was happening.
Because imagine if we didn't have that.
Imagine if we didn't have the Old Testament for a second.
Christ had just come and done miracles and he...
people and they'd been crucified and then risen from the dead and ascended into
heaven. Right. It would it would just be contextless actions. Right. You know,
they would be impressive, you know, but but what would we what would we do going
forward to participate in that and and celebrate that? How would we comprehend
that how would we find a way into that right? We couldn't.
We couldn't, right? And so that is when we talk about patterns in the Old Testament being filled
up to overflowing in the New Testament, that's not a handy dodge or a weird principle or just, you know,
symbolism happens or whatever, right? We're talking about a sort of a concrete thing of God preparing
people to be able to understand what he did in Christ and is doing in Christ.
Yeah.
Alright, well we're gonna go ahead and take our second break and when we come back we're going to talk about what it means for us to be baptized.
So we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment.
Take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
I'm Joel Miller, and I'm Jamie Bennett.
It's one of the last books the Old Testament in terms of when it was written, and yet part
of it is written in the style of the great king Solomon who was renowned for his love
of wisdom.
The church fathers loved this book.
Jerome quoted it more than 80 times, and Augustine quoted it almost 800 times.
The reason is actually pretty clear.
Life in this world is a mystery.
Worst, it's also tough.
And because life in this world is tough,
a book like The Wisdom of Solomon,
which is the book we're talking about,
helps explain what we're going through,
why we're going through it,
and also who we're going through it with.
That's right.
On our podcast, Bad Books of the Bible,
We're talking about the wisdom of sol-
in this season. It's basically a Bible study on a podcast taking a couple chapters at a time,
right here on H and Faith radio. We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung. If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio. You know, hearing that ad makes me think that you should do a Bible study
podcast.
Stephen, have you thought about it?
Yeah, believe it or not, last night, last night, uh, less than 24 hours ago, I finished
my first pass through the whole Bible.
You did it.
In real time, 12 and a half years later.
Wow.
From Genesee to Revelation.
Oh, that's a hand.
I could hear John Good.
and saying that. Well, congratulations. So yeah, so now I got to start over with Genesis,
because we didn't record Genesis last time, which is actually good because it would have been terrible.
Back when you were still in your 30s, I would have pulled it down anyway. I didn't know anything 12 and
a half years ago. Wow. Yeah, I mean, on the podcast for a whole council of God in terms of what's
what's being released, it just started first job.
Yeah, so I think we're, you know.
Maybe two or three months behind, I think, on the podcast.
Probably.
Yeah.
Revelation took a minute.
I'll bet.
You can just tell everybody read, see an injure of Cicero.
Basically.
Yeah.
You can just say that.
Well, it's very disappointing because there's nothing about China in there actually, or
Moscow or America's place in biblical prophecy.
Yeah.
Well, that actually isn't there, but not in a way that anybody's going to like.
Is that when the vieting comes up out of the water?
No, that's more like Babylon, that nice young lady.
Just drunk out the blood of the saints.
That's exciting.
All right. Well, we're back. Feel free to give us a call.
We will still take your calls. Now we're talking about
Christian baptism. So first we talked about circumcision and then in the second half we talked about the baptism of John the
Forerunner and Baptist and now we're talking about Christian baptism. So true to form, right? You know the thing that our episode is about we finally get to it in the third half.
Yeah, and that was circumcision in general, not Christian circumcision because
That's you be hard pressed to find a Christian oil I think
It's true
Because now that I'm thinking of any that's probably
is a thing. Okay, now we need to find out. If you're listening to this and you are a Christian
oil, email Father Andrew, and should pay with your, I'm googling Christian oil right now.
Yeah. Anyway. So, but yes, now we're talking about Christian baptism per se.
Because
usual, it is in our third half when we get to our actual topic. So at the core, as we've
already seen, like in St. Paul's writings about us being buried with Christ in baptism,
right, dying of Christ in baptism, rising again to do life, that if we want to talk about
what's going, what baptism is doing, right? Then at a very basic level, baptism is about
A movement from...
death to life through water. And because of that, as we're just saying at the end of the second half,
the apostles in the New Testament are going to look at these patterns that are established
in the Old Testament as ways of understanding what's now going on in.
baptism into Christ.
Okay.
And so one of these that we talked about at length, right,
in one of our Pascar episodes,
has to do with the crossing of the Red Sea,
or the Sea of Reads, right, with Moses.
And we talked about how the Sea of Reads in Egyptian stories
was something that had to be crossed
cross in order to get to the after.
life, and that they would offer sort of incantations and various ritual offerings to get the gods to sort of
bring them across the sea of reads safely into the afterlife. There was the possibility of becoming
entangled in the reads and becoming one of the drowned ones, which was essentially their name for
the damped. Yeah, right. And so both in the
the story is narrated in Exodus, but then especially the way it's described in
Exodus 15 in the song of the sea, it is directly connected to these traditions in
these stories. So this isn't, right, like we're going to quote St. Paul and
First Corinthians here in a minute who makes this comparison. St. Paul's just
not coming up with an allegory or an analogy. He's definitely not saying the
original thing didn't happen.
Right. Right. But he's reading what happened there in terms of what it originally meant, that this
was for the Israelites a passage from death to life through water, that they were passing through
the realm of death safely, unlike the Egyptians who ended up being the drowned ones. Yeah, right.
Right, and they were being right delivered in this in this real sense. Right, so the most prominent place
where St. Paul refers to this, at least the most explicit one, is in 1 Corinthians 10,
right at the beginning of the chapter. Yeah, okay. So verses 1 and 2,
Freud do not want you to be unaware brothers, that our fathers were all under the cloud and all
passed through the sea, and all were baptized into Moses in the cloud and in the sea.
I probably the phrase, it's maybe weird to people as being baptized into Moses.
Right.
Wait, what?
Yeah, like I don't know what's going on in the Greek there, but you know, like wait,
wait, that's a pretty straightforward translation.
Christ baptized into Moses.
So St. Paul says many things that are hard to understand.
I've heard that.
So we'll put a pin in the cloud part for now.
See future.
christmas episode. But the C part obviously is a little more clear. Right. So this
baptized into Moses part has to do with the way this is seen as sort of one event.
Right. So the Passover, the Exodus out of Egypt and then coming to Mount Sinai
eye and the
receiving of the of the Torah are
intimately connected.
Okay. Right. And this is similar to the way in which for us as
as Orthodox Christians and I think for most Christians who have
any kind of like liturgical sense.
the way that that PASCA that Easter that
Christ resurrection and Pentecost.
Because remember Pentecost originally was the giving of the Torah, the giving of the law.
The way those two events are sort of connected.
They move together on the calendar.
They represent their own cycle over against the fixed feasts.
They sort of form this unit together.
So it was in the same way.
And as we, as we saw.
saw when we were taking things, St. Paul said about circumcision and baptism, he sees baptism
as then immediately connected to faithfulness. In the same way that circumcision, going all
the way back to Abraham, was immediately connected to faithfulness.
Yeah, right.
It's your circumcised and walk before me and be righteous, right?
so he's connecting those who...
are baptized in the cloud in the sea, right, to those who are then called to keep the Torah when
it is given. And Moses is used there because Moses is sort of the mediator of that covenant to the
people. Yeah, he's the instrument by which it's happening. Right. So this is effectively about them
being baptized into the Torah. Yeah. Right. That...
this event establishes now this relationship. Right? And that's why in 1 Corinthians 10,
if you go on, Passover's 2, where we read Saint Paul the reason he starts this with,
I do not want you to be unaware of brothers. I'm reminding you guys that after that happened,
And those who were faithless died in the wilderness.
They were left behind.
And so he's saying to them, yes, you were all baptized into Christ, but if that does
now become a life of faithfulness, then that baptism by itself isn't going to do you
any more good than it did those who died in the wilderness,
in disobedience, right?
And so remember the Torah contained both blessings and curses of that of the covenant.
So baptism is the beginning, right, in that sense of that that life of faithfulness.
Yeah, it's a new life, not just a badge.
Right, right, or a status.
Yeah.
So the other major sort of old testament pattern that gets brought forward is a way to help
understand Christian baptism. And now we're going to go with St. Peter is the flood of Noah.
And that's because it's about water, right? Yes, that's it. That's the only
that's all there is to it so that means that all you think with water in it.
that about baptism now.
All the people who died in the flood are being baptized.
Anytime you see a stick of wood in the Old Testament,
that's the cross.
As Nietzsche joked.
But no, that's not what we're saying.
Right?
Say Peter is gonna make a much more involved connection than that.
Yes, okay.
So, and this is actually the passage
where we get the title for our episode tonight.
So first Peter chapter three.
verses 18-22.
For Christ also suffered once for sins, the righteous for the unrighteous, that He might bring
us to God, being put to death in the flesh but made alive in the Spirit, in which He
went and proclaimed to the Spirits in prison, because they formerly did not obey, when
God's patience waited in the days of Noah, while the ark was being prepared, in which
A few that is 8 persons were brought safely through water.
Bap.
which corresponds to this now saves you,
not as a removal of dirt from the body,
but as an appeal to God for a good conscience
through the resurrection of Jesus Christ,
who has gone into heaven
and is at the right hand of God
with angels, authorities, and powers
having been subjected to him.
There's a lot going on in that passage.
Yeah.
But I think it's pretty self-explanatory.
It's got difficult, like, say, Paul.
Okay, good night, everybody.
Um, so...
Right, so we're focusing, of course, on this baptism element, but it's important that
we see that Saint Peter has this whole narration before he says baptism, which corresponds to
this.
To this, yeah.
So it's not just the last word of verse 20.
water and then 21 baptism which corresponds to this, corresponds to water, see water, right?
That's not what he's doing, right? So he is telling the story of Christ descent into Hades,
right? And in that descent into Hades, I know we've talked about this on the show before,
but it's been a while.
Oh yeah.
Yes.
In that descent into Hades, he confronts...
these spirits who are imprisoned there, right, and makes this proclamation to them. And we've
talked about how this mirrors in the book of Enic, Enic's dissent to the imprisoned watchers,
right, where they kind of ask Enic to help get them off the hook, not because they're actually
repentant, but just they don't like being imprisoned, right? So they say, hey, can you make it,
God likes you
you, Enic, you're a righteous man. Can you make an appeal for us? Right? It's a God. And so Enic,
being a good guy does, and God sends Enic back to tell them nope, right? You guys are staying here.
Until the end of days, when you'll get thrown into the lake of fire, right? So you have that to look
forward to. But this is the same kind of thing here, right? Because which spirits are these who
Christ makes the Proclamation.
to. It's the spirit of the the disobedient of the days of Noah. Yeah, though these are
dead giants. Yes, these are Nephilim. These are watchers, right? This is directly what St. Peter is
referring to. And in 2 Peter, he refers to the book of the even more obviously than this.
But so it's those particular
spirits, right, that he makes this proclamation to of their doom, right, and then, right,
Noah is sort of was sort of saved out of that world through water, right. So notice,
after he says baptism, which corresponds to this, meaning all of that, that whole narrative,
He ends
the passage we read by talking about Christ having ascended into heaven with the
angels' authorities and powers subjected to Him. So angelic beings are
still closely in view in what St. Peter is talking about. So when we come to the
baptism now saves you. Right? The correct question to ask is saved from what?
Hmm.
Right. Yeah.
From in the...
here is definitely evil spirits and good spirits. Right. Right. And so what was Noah
saved from? Noah was saved from those people who those people, those beings, those spiritual
beings, evil spiritual beings, to whom Christ proclaimed their doom when he passed through the
underworld. Yeah, which just underlines once again that the gospel isn't good news for everybody.
So Christ passes from death to life.
Noah passes...
from, right, this world of evil, right, through water to life, right? And now we also are saved from
the powers of evil, right, through baptism. And is then the beginning of just as after baptism,
after he mentions baptism. Christ's story can
continues with his Ascent into Heaven and his enthronement.
Baptism also for us is the beginning of our life of theosis, our life of becoming like
Christ, being conformed to his image, which culminates in the enthronement of humanity,
right?
Because as Hebrews says, it is not to angels that God has subjected the world to come.
Yeah, I mean, see also every reference to thrones and plural we've ever made.
I don't know.
Let's see also one of my favorite verses to quote
that we become equal to the angels, Luke 2036.
I mean, this is just everywhere that all this theosis,
language, all over the scripture in terms of being
enthroned with Christ and being stewards
of the life of the world to come.
Right.
And so there is contained then within baptism,
this element of spiritual warfare.
Yeah, this idea of entering into a declaration.
of war against the evil spiritual powers. This is why in Orthodox tradition we
spit on the devil on at with the devil. Sorry, that was a Lutheran joke.
In with and under. Sorry. At at at the devil right there is this element of
When someone comes to be baptized they are now
entering into spiritual warfare.
Yeah.
Yeah, which I mean, it's underlined very much, for instance,
the beginning of baptism in Greek is called the Apotaxis and the Sindaxes,
which means basically coming away from the ordering in which you were
and now being reordered along with Christ.
You know, the idea is you're leaving behind the devil and his
hoes.
and joining the Lord of hosts himself.
I mean, I think that those are actually military terms.
I'm not sure.
But it often, of course, is described as, you know,
in sermons about it as being enlisted with Christ
and all that kind of thing.
Yeah.
So,
a couple things before we end the episode.
own. Right.
related to baptism. First another what baptism is not. And this stems from, this is also something
that St. Paul addresses to the church in Corinth, that baptism into Moses as mediator.
There was a confusion apparently in the Corinthian church. That was leading to so
bad results in terms of how they viewed baptism and what baptism was doing that's related to
both of the things we just talked about, not just the idea of being baptized in DeMoses,
but also the idea of sort of you're now on this team in this fight. Yeah. Right. Exactly how those
teams are designated. Yeah, yeah, so, you know, this we're just continuing on and
Yeah, first Corinthians chapter one, yeah, yeah, this is earlier.
Sorry.
Chapter one versus 10 through 17.
And you'll recognize us, everybody.
I appeal to you, brothers, by the name of our Lord Jesus Christ,
that all of you agree and that there be no divisions among you,
but that you be united in the same mind and in the same judgment.
For it has been reported to me by Chloe's people
that there is quarreling among you, my brothers.
What I mean is that each one of you says,
I follow Paul or I follow Apalus or I follow...
Seifis or I follow Christ.
Is Christ divided?
Was Paul crucified for you?
Or were you baptized in the name of Paul?
I thank God that I baptized none of you
except Christmas and Gaius so that no one may say
that you were baptized in my name.
I did baptize also the household of Stephanus.
Beyond that, I do not know whether I baptized anyone else.
For Christ did not send me to baptize,
but to preach the gospel.
And to not with words of eloquent wisdom,
the cross of Christ be emptied of its power.
Hmm.
One of the reasons I really like this passage is that you can tell how close it is to St. Paul's
dictation, right?
Because he's literally like, boy, I'm glad I didn't baptize anybody except this guy,
this guy.
Well, okay, there was also that guy, right?
Maybe this other guy.
Okay, I don't know if I baptized anybody else, but anyway, you get my point, right?
Right.
Yeah.
he's, you know, this is a straight forward.
sense here, which is saying like there's not sects within the church. There's not, you know,
I mean, we can have schools of thought on some level, but it shouldn't be teams.
Right. And Christ is the mediator. Right.
Between God and man.
Our loyalty is to Christ, not to any human teacher or
leader, or whether they have a high and exalted ecclesiastical position or a gigantic following
on the internet. Our loyalty is not to any of them as Christians.
Right. And this is what St. Paul's getting at. I mean, it may sound weird at first when
he says, for Christ did not send me to baptize, but to preach the gospel. Because your brain
might go to Matthew 28 right in the Great Commission where Christ says go.
disciples of all nations baptizing them, right? Kind of sounds like he
sent in the apostles to baptize, right? Yeah. But that's not what St. Paul's
getting at. What he's getting at is that he wasn't sent out to make
Paulians. Yes. Paul. He wasn't sent out, you know,
Christianity and evangelism is not like Amway.
Adjust to clarify, I'm not saying anything negative about Amway.
It's time not like me.
vaguely suggesting that if one were to diagram the structure of the organization on a piece
of paper, it would be very narrow at the top and wide at the bottom.
That's all I'm saying.
That's like some shape we might have heard of before.
Send your emails to fatherandru at angiefaith.com.
Yeah.
And legal.
I think that's not a really serious thing.
It'd go through him.
But that's not...
Right, that's not what it's about.
It was not making followers for himself.
Yeah, which, unfortunately, which is about Christ.
About Christ.
Yeah, unfortunately, that's, you know, Sally,
that's a thing amongst people who call themselves Christians.
And, you know, like, I don't think I've really seen this,
but I hope that no one ever out there is like,
well, I'm a Lord of spirits listener.
And like, you know, like, you know,
that's not a thing, people.
That's not a thing.
Well, it's not what, what this is about,
Where?
pointing you to Christ, reporting you to life in parishes.
It's not about which team you're on or who you follow on whatever.
That's not this is it at all part of what was behind my stop sipping ramp a few
episodes ago.
Yeah.
And this is the real.
It's not just that like, oh, some I hear somebody say there are others,
even the young fan and I'm uncomfortable with it.
I mean, I am, but that's not.
Let's...
That's not what I'm getting at. The place where this rubber meets the road and this happens all the time in the life of the Orthodox Church and pretty much all other Christian communities and non-Christian communities is people get put in this position of leadership or prominence or whatever it is.
And people don't even realize they're doing it.
They're starting to put their loyalty and their trust in those people.
And the rubber meets the rubber.
when those people let you down.
Yeah.
When those people mess up, right?
This is why I don't want symptoms.
This is why I don't want people
being like, I'm a father, Steven D. Young van,
because I will let you down.
I will mess up, right?
Eventually I'll succeed at getting myself canceled.
Right?
Eventually I will say something that offends you, right?
Like maybe you thought I was great
and now I just took a shot at Amway for no reason.
Yeah.
Right?
But whatever it is, eventually it'll happen.
And I don't want that to cause you to leave the Orthodox Church.
I don't want that to drive you away from Christ.
That's why I don't want it.
Yeah.
And there's a flip side to this too, which is that people who attach themselves to some
figure and loyalty then are incapable of noticing when they do mess up.
You know, they end up making excuses for all kinds of bad behavior.
And then...
kind of another flip side of it is like well when you see someone do mess up then you kind of denounce
their Christianity entirely. You know like well he's just one of the bad ones because he did this one
thing or said this one thing or whatever it might be because all of this is to absolutize individual
people when it's Christ who is the absolute. And so then we can if we have Christ's or absolute
then we can say this is a good action or a good word this is a bad action or a bad word
and
because it's all judged by Christ and not by which team you're on.
It's such a toxic way to be and we all do this, right?
We all do it, whether it's, you know, teachers in the church or on the internet or politics, right?
This happens all the time, you know.
I'm on this person's team or I'm this person's friend and so therefore,
or I'm not on their team, not their friend, so everything they do is bad.
You know that just shows that we need to re-earn
ourselves towards Christ, whenever we behave that way. We all do it. So let's all repent.
You know? Yeah. Yeah. I hope that within my deluge of content, I pour out
continuously. There are things that are helpful to people. Right? But those are things
that will be found amidst that content. That's not me as a person. Me as a person, Father Stephen
in India, I will become a stumbling block for you eventually.
Yeah.
I'm not a very good person.
So just accept that now, right?
But because God was able to speak through Baelum's ass,
hopefully some good things for you will come out of me.
Yeah. And so, you know, the point here is that baptism does not
make people, do not put people into a sect.
It's into Christ who is the savior of the world.
Yeah, you know, yeah.
And so sort of a summary of what we've been talking about now, right?
Because ritual does something, right?
It doesn't represent something.
It's not a performance for you to view of something.
It's not giving you food for thought.
It's actually doing something.
What does baptism do in summary, right?
all the kind of concepts we've been talking about.
about. Baptism removes a person from the world.
Yeah, and we should emphasize it's the sense of the world that we are talking about earlier,
you know, the sort of the world system of evil and darkness and demons.
Right. Not the creation. Right. Right. The world, the flesh and the devil.
Right. That sense of world. Right. Um, the source of sin, right, separated from that.
And therefore by that separation made holy, sanctified, right?
It is.
as we were just saying, a declaration of spiritual warfare.
It is the death of the person who went into the water and the new life of the person who
comes out, the beginning of the life of the one who comes out.
I tell people when I receive them into the church, whether it's baptism or chrismation,
However, it happens that there is no reason why the day after they've been baptized.
they have to be the same person they were the day before.
Anything they want to leave behind, they can leave in the water and start over.
It is the beginning of membership in the family of God, the big extended family.
That includes all of us.
it makes us co-airs in Christ, meaning all of the promises of
Christ, he shares with us when we're baptized into Christ.
As we talked about, all of these things, right?
And there's Naria, one of them that infants don't need going back to that question.
Yeah, right.
To be beginning of the second half, right?
So after that summary, I feel we must include this brief appendix.
Okay, about baptism for the dead.
baptism for the dead. Right. And of course, we're referring to what St. Paul refers to in
1 Corinthians 15 as part of his argument about the resurrection. Yes, this is this is a completely
non-controversial and totally clear verse. Yes. He says otherwise, what do people mean by being
baptized on behalf of the dead? If the dead are not raised at all, why are people baptized on their
their behalf.
So they'd call some time.
says things that are hard to understand. So to give this a little context, right, that
chapter 15 of 1 Corinthians is really all about the resurrection of the dead.
Yeah. Right. And why is this something that Saint Paul has to address? Well, as we were saying
in the first half. The Christian community in Corinth has two types of folks.
There's Christians from a Jewish background.
There's Christians from a pagan Gentile background.
And for the, the pagans,
the idea of the bodily resurrection was kind of ludicrous.
Yeah, right.
I mean, literally this is what happens in Athens
in Acts 17 with St. Paul,
like everybody's kind of vibing with him
until he brings up the bodily resurrection
and they all laugh at him.
Yeah.
That's just like why would you want that?
that, right? Why would you want to be in a body again, right?
On the side of Jewish Christians, while there were, like for example, the Pharisees, there
were prominent groups within Second Temple Judaism that believed in the bodily resurrection.
There were also some that did not, right?
The Sadducees did not.
Other group.
dinned or had different ideas about what an afterlife might look like that didn't include a bodily
resurrection per se. So a subset of those Jewish Christians would be familiar with the idea of bodily
resurrection, but not all of them necessarily. And so St. Paul in this lengthy chapter
sets out trying to argue for it. And he argues for it on all number of bounds. Like if you did
physical resurrection, then you're saying Christ wasn't physically raised from the dead.
But then here's all the things that would result from that being the case. He goes at it from
different angles. And so the verse, you just read 15 verse 29 is one of his, right, many arguments
that he has lined up, where he refers to this practice that the community and Corinth at least
is familiar with that
There were people who were being, as it's translated,
they're baptism on behalf of the dead.
The Greek preposition there that's translated
is on behalf of.
Greek prepositions are pretty flexible.
This one can mean on behalf of it.
Really, the core of it is for the benefit of.
Right?
And so, it's not that on behalf of is wrong.
That's what we do.
one way it could be used, but not the only way. Right. All we know is that the
baptism of these people is somehow benefiting the dead, right? Or it's somehow
connected in a positive way from what they're doing to the dead, right? In that
direction. And then he falls out with, if the dead are not raised at all, why are
people about.
on their behalf. So whatever this practice means, right, it would make no sense if the resurrection
isn't real. Right. Right. So to understand this, and I know I've talked about this distinction
on the show before, but St. Paul is very particular about when he uses dead in the plural,
right? Necree. And when he puts the article in front of it.
So in English, we would portray that as dead versus the dead.
When St. Paul uses it without the article, just dead in the plural, he means all the dead people.
It just dead people in general, right?
When he uses the article, which we'd
would translate as the dead. The article in Greek is really still kind of functioning
partially as a demonstrative pronoun. So you could sort of over translate it as these dead
idea being he's referring to a specific group of dead people, not just to dead people in
general. That's what the article does, right? It makes it so those dead. Right. So if you
track when Saint Paul uses it with and
without the article. What you find is when he uses it with the article to refer to a specific
group of dead, he's referring to dead Christians, referring to the dead faithful or the dead of
the old covenant, the righteous dead of the old covenant. But it's always sort of that
category of the righteous dead, right? So this isn't people being baptized on behalf of
dead people in general.
It's people being baptized on behalf of
of these righteous dead, right, and dead Christians, right? So that means it can't
mean what our Mormon friends would want it to mean, right? Because the the
Latter-day Saints practice is that people who are members of the LDS are baptized
for someone who wasn't.
with the idea that that makes them now baptized.
Right, which is why they're super duper into genealogy to try to retroactively include all of their dead relatives in the LDS church.
Right.
And so it can't mean that, right?
Because then St. Paul wouldn't use the article.
Hmm.
Right, so the fact that he's using the article, these are already faithful people.
So these are people who presumably would be
and paradise would be in the positive afterlife. These are the people who
Saint Paul calls the dead in Christ, right, who are with Christ. So they don't
need to be baptized, right? So then what is this relationship that's being set up?
This corresponds to the idea in Roman culture of patronage. Right. So
So...
When this is how people got educated,
not just in terms of education the way we would think of it,
maybe, but also like trade,
like we would think of a trade school, right?
That kind of stuff costs money.
Any kind of education in the Roman world costs money, right?
Peasants didn't get any education.
We're no public schools, right?
So, and so most people did not have the money
they needed to go and do that.
and so
So they would have a patron who would be an older, established person, often established
within that trait or within that discipline, that the person was pursuing who would effectively
sponsor them, right, who sort of sponsor them, guide them, pay for what they needed.
And then in return, the person who was being patronized, pardon the pun.
would the things he would do at least for a certain period of time, at least while the
patron was alive, would be done in that patron's name.
Right.
So, the closest thing we have to this in the modern day, right, is when you watch shows
on PBS or listen to NPR podcasts or something, they say, this was made possible by a grant
from, right, whatever.
So you're kind of giving them credit for your work, right?
So if you were an artisan and you had a patron
and you would create something and you would say, you know,
this is by virtue of my patron.
So it's so, and that would bring honor, right?
And sort of respect and glory to the patron, right?
And so the idea here that St. Paul is getting at is that
There were people already, already.
at this point, and we're talking about 25 years after the death and resurrection of Christ,
because there were already martyrs, etc., unfortunately, who were being baptized and who were
taking the names of departed saints.
He talks about, there is a subgroup of people who are doing this.
It's not everyone does it to this yet.
This is common practice now in the Orthodox Church that you take a patron saint.
But this is what Saint Paul is referring to in his very earliest stage.
The idea being, obviously, a saint in glory is more advanced on the path, right,
of following Christ than I am by a lot.
And so you take this patron saint, you establish this relationship with that patron saint.
and they both...
service, sort of a guide to you and what you do within the church community, you are
doing in their name.
There's this connection.
So mystery unlocked, that's what's going on for the first Corinthians 1520.
Yeah.
I mean, it's a fast, at least in a short version.
There's a much longer version of that argument.
you do it.
Yeah, I mean, it makes sense to me.
So, yeah, yeah.
All right, well, to wrap up our baptism episode this evening.
And before we do that, actually, I just want to make a note to everybody that we, as I said
at the beginning, we're doing a series now on the Holy Mysteries, the Sacrifice of the
Church.
We're going to continue doing that with the next episode.
The next episode, however, is going to be pre-recorded.
So you won't be able to call in next time, although as Father Stephen said, we're going
remind you, if you do call in, who knows what might happen, but we will not be on the
other end of the line.
So talk to you, that's for sure.
No matter what else might happen.
But we're going to continue next time.
So just a note that next time it'll be aired live, but it won't be us.
It'll just be a pre-recorded episode.
So well, to wrap up our baptism episode, you know, one of the big past the role questions
that parish priests especially deal with.
But I don't think it's just an issue.
for the pastor, it's really an issue for the whole community, is that there are people
who will come to the church, and they'll especially have their child baptized, or they
might come to the church because they're maybe going to get married or something like that,
and be baptized themselves.
And then that's often the last time you see them.
This happens a lot.
In fact, I would be willing to bet.
that there are more, at least in the United States,
and probably in other countries too,
but I'm pretty sure about the United States,
that there are more people who have had baptism
in the church who are not in the church than are in the church.
And it's a vexing issue.
It happens all the time.
And we do all kinds of things to try to mitigate that,
try to prevent it from happening.
You know, when I was still pastoring one of the things
that I would do is I would tell people,
especially who weren't part of the church community already,
you know, I wanted to see them come to church for a while
before I would be willing to put the baptism
of their child on the schedule.
I would say yes, we'll baptize that child,
but this child needs to be raised in the church.
And so show me that you're gonna do that.
You know, there's all kinds of ways that this kid's done.
and...
I think what this betrays is this idea that baptism is what we have talked about in other
episodes as a kind of religious technique, which if you do it just the right way, then
you get a particular result.
And if you don't do it the right way, then you're not going to get that result.
In other words, that it's a kind of magic.
And I think that this way of looking at it is pretty rampant, actually.
And it's not just evidence by the fact that there are people who treat it like a magical spell that gets into heaven
or that gives you a membership or something like that.
But it's also evidence by the fact that there are a lot of debates that happen, largely between people
Who are not actually qualified to have the debate?
just because they're not trained and knowledgeable, although that's often the case, but because
they're not the ones actually making the decisions and not the ones actually responsible for
the decisions about, and this was a referenced in the question we got an email about, especially
the reception of, of converts into the church, people with a Christian background who, in
many cases have experienced a baptism ritual within that previous
Christian experience. And so there is a particular distortion, for instance, and I'm just going
to come right out and say this because it is a distortion, absolutely distortion, of so-called
corrective baptism. That is people who have been received into the Orthodox Church, who
Bishop received them, usually through a priest, and they've been receiving Holy Communion,
And then they go and get baptized by somebody else.
Right.
And there's.
all kinds of ways that that manifests. But this is a distortion because if you look at the
actual history of the church and the way that it is dealt with this question, there's not a single formula.
And the way that we can we know that is by reading the actual canons of the ecumenical councils that
say, receive these converts in this way, receive these converts in this way, receive these other
the comments in this way.
And if you...
compile them all together and try to come up with some kind of
mechanistic theory about how it's supposed to work. It just
doesn't actually all work out in any kind of codifiable way.
It doesn't. There's just no sort of
machine that you can put together that is sort of the baptism machine that it works this way
and not this other way.
And I think the attempt to do that is...
once again, to treat baptism as a kind of religious technique that it's so sort of magic and
you have to do it in an exact certain perfect way. And if you don't, then it doesn't work.
There's simply nothing, you know, whatever that happened. It backfires or whatever.
But as we've seen, by all this examination we've had of Scripture, the point of baptism,
there's many things that it accomplishes. But one of the things that it accomplishes is to bring
you into the family of God so that you can live in right.
This is, this goes all the way back to the covenant with Abraham and continues on.
It's, as we mentioned, it's the, it's the first commandment that is a kind of foundational.
This is how you live commandment.
It's commandment of faithfulness.
And, you know, as we said at the beginning of, I came in for this half or the second half,
that for someone to say, well, this is the way I want to be received and not this way
is to begin the whole thing with disobedience, to begin the whole thing being self will.
and with individualism, and to judge the way that another bishop chooses to apply the
commandments and the canons is, again, being self-willed and individualistic, right?
As it says in Scripture very explicitly, who are you to judge another man's servant?
And worse, who are you to judge another man's master, literally?
the point is to bring someone into this life.
of faithfulness. And at the end of time, we know that every person is going to be judged
according to what he has done, according to what he has done. And that's why questions
about, well, can someone really be saved if they have not received baptism at all or in
a particular way, betrays this kind of mechanistic religious technique approach to this holy
sacrament into all the sacraments in a lot of ways.
to turn it into a kind of materialistic, frankly, formula. And that's not what it is.
Now, by saying that, I'm not saying that the way that you do it doesn't matter,
I'm not saying that at all. But I am saying that within the
two millennial long consciousness of the church and how to bring people into faithfulness,
that it's gotten applied in different ways, different places, different times, different groups of
people and to it.
attempt to come up with a one-size-fits-all approach to these things is to condemn whole swaths
of church history and holy people, in fact. And that's not what we do as Orthodox Christians.
We don't do that. Instead, we enter into the church as it is, and we are obedient to
the community that we enter into. And if we're not ready to be obedient within that, then
We need to repat and become ready to be obedient.
And the reason for all of that is, as we've said, that it's about entering into this life of faithfulness.
Not a faithfulness to any particular theory, not a faithfulness to any particular preferred commenter or teacher, or whoever,
not a faithfulness to a particular charismatic speaker, or very smart person, or whatever, it's faithfulness to Christ.
Faithfulness to Christ. And we've seen that faithfulness to Christ can be done in a lot of different ways throughout the history of the Church.
church. There's a consistency between
all of them. There's a consistency between all of them, but it's not a consistency of technique
you know that you have to get everything technically correct in a certain kind of way or else
it just doesn't work. Instead what we see is people orienting themselves towards Christ.
And so I believe that baptism of course is a great place to talk about all of this
because it's so...
full of so many things, the summary that Father Stephen gave
there at the end, that brings all this stuff together,
that's to try to reduce it down to some kind of formula
or a technique, is to really do violence to what is being
joined to Christ, to what is becoming co-heirs with Christ,
to what is entering into that whole life in the family of God.
And what an amazing and awesome
awesome gift. It is from God to be welcomed into his kingdom. Father Stephen? Yeah, to kind of kick off from that.
The problem of individualism is very real. And it afflicks all of us. Again, this is one of those things that's come into us from our culture.
It's been built into us and just the way we see things in terms of how we see ourselves,
how we see the church, right, our parish is a collection of people, a collection of individuals.
And it lends itself to a whole view of the Christian life.
very different than the view that's presented by the scriptures. When I say
the scriptures, I mean old and new testament as we've been seeing tonight, that
those are not really all that far apart. Because we've kind of boiled down
Christianity and a lot of our heads to, here's a list of things I have to believe,
meaning I have to give my assent to True Falls Test Style.
And then here are a list of moral rules I have to follow.
And among the moral rules, there are big ones that are not negotiable and then some smaller
ones that are maybe negotiable.
But that's not, again, that's completely individualized.
That's an overview of religion that's what's going on in my head and what are the things
that I'm not supposed to do as an individual.
and that's totally foreign.
to what we get in the scriptures, what we get in the historic Christian faith
for, I'll say most of its history to be polite.
And breaking that down is very hard for all of us.
Right? It's very hard for all of us.
We look at churches.
Right on one hand. Well, this is a moral duty. I'm supposed to go to church. I'm supposed to go to literature
I mean at least on Sundays at least most Sundays right?
Um, I'm supposed to so I should so I really should if I don't I'll feel bad
go to confession confess not having come to church. Um
Not really or and we look at it as well. I'm gonna go I'm gonna receive communion. I'm going to pray
Hopefully I'll hear a good homily, but that's like flipping a coin a lot of the time.
Hopefully I'll get something out of it, right?
As an individual, if that I find that part lacking, if I'm, if I didn't do what I was supposed
to do, so I'm not going to be able to receive communion or if I feel like I'm not going
to get anything out of it, if the homilies are always not that great and I don't feel
I'm gonna get anything out of it then that will quickly overwhelm the duty part.
And as Father Andrew was just talking about, we even view baptism in the beginning of the
Christian life that way, is what is it doing to and for me as an individual?
And how do I have to do it and when should I do it to sort of maximize that benefit or
make sure it's real or make sure it takes, make sure it does what I want it to do, right?
Baptism
is entering into a way of life that is not individual.
Even if you are living a very individualistic way of life before,
that's one of the things that needs to die in the water.
Baptism is entering into a way of life that involves others,
that involves the rest of the Christian community.
Immediately the rest of the parish family into which you are.
baptized and then into the broader, huge extended family of the whole church and then even beyond that,
all through the ages. Right? Say Paul in 1 Corinthians 10 says, our fathers were baptized in
De Moses. And if you read a little further that chapter, it becomes very clear he's speaking to
former pagans, but they're now part of the family, so they're their fathers too.
way of life that we enter into. And it is impossible to keep the commandments of
Christ by yourself. You can't love your neighbor as yourself by yourself. You
can't even love God with all your heart, soul, mind, and strength by yourself.
Because part of your heart and part of your soul and even your mind and even your
strength has to do with what and who you love and who you care about and offering
that to God as well. Those are the first two we can go on and on, right? To show love
you have to have someone to love. Joy is shared. You can't be at peace alone
because peace implies that there are other parties with whom you are at peace.
You definitely can't be a peacemaker by yourself.
All of what we are called to, all of the things that are constitutive of the Christian life,
of the way of life that leads to salvation in all of its senses,
require us to be living in a community with other people,
with whom we disagree about things, with whom we don't always get along,
whose personalities rub us the wrong way.
Right
nothing heroic about loving someone who does nothing but flatter you and tell you how wonderful you are.
There's nothing heroic about being with people who never actually need your help.
There's nothing heroic about being part of a community that never stretches you in any direction in any way.
And so if we're serious
about becoming like Christ, who did not live as a hermit, who lived his
life surrounded by people. Pretty much all of whom did not understand him, a
massive proportion of whom hated him who ended up murdering him for various
reasons. If we want to be like him, then we have to live the way he lived and
and we have
have to be with other people.
That's how we find our salvation.
Because it's not just in this life that we're here
to support each other, to learn from each other,
to struggle with each other, to strive with each other,
to have the sharp edges of ourselves broken off
in the rock tumbler that is a church community.
It's not just here and now in this life.
But it's when we stand before Christ one day.
We're not going to be standing there alone.
We're going to be standing there shoulder to shoulder
with these same people who we've lived our life with.
To give an account for who we were to them
and what we did and didn't do for them
and for them to give testimony to who we are
and what we've done in this life.
So we're not in this alone.
That makes this harder in some ways.
It makes it more beautiful in some ways.
And it helps in some ways.
But we are pursuing salvation together.
And baptism is the beginning of that, being baptized and brought into this family.
Amen.
Well, that's our show for tonight, everyone.
Thank you very much for listening.
If you didn't call us tonight.
We'd still love to hear from you.
You can email us at LordofSpiritz.nz and faith.com.
You can message us at our Facebook page or you can leave us a voicemail at SpeakPipe.com
slash LordofSpiritz.
And join us for a live broadcast of the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7
PM Eastern 4 PM Pacific.
Except Thanksgiving, when we'll be talking about the Eucharist pre-recorded.
And then after that, baptism of fire.
If you're on Facebook, you can like our page and join our discussion group, leave reviews
and ratings everywhere, but most importantly...
please share the show with a friend who is going to benefit from it.
And finally be sure to go to www.engsrefate.com
Stroke Support and help make sure we and lots of other AFR
podcasters stay on the air and remember pain lies on the river side.
Thank you, good night and may God bless you all.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father
Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of
Ancient Faith Radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 than thousands of thousands,
with a loud voice, worthy is the land that was
It is lame to receive power and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11-12